<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mvltvm in parvo, aut vox veritatis wherein the principles, practices, and transactions of the English nation, but more especially and in particular by their representatives assembled in Parliament anno Domini 1640, 1641 : as also, 1681 are most faithfully and impartially examined, collected, and compared together for the present seasonable use, benefit and information of the publick : as also the wonderful and most solemn manner and form of ratifying, confirming and pronouncing of that most dreadful curse and execration against the violators and infringers of Magna Charta in the time of Henry the Third, King of England, &amp;c. ... / by Theophilus Rationalis ...</title>
            <author>Rationalis, Theophilus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51589</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32098</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12322505</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12322505</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59492</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51589)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59492)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1019:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mvltvm in parvo, aut vox veritatis wherein the principles, practices, and transactions of the English nation, but more especially and in particular by their representatives assembled in Parliament anno Domini 1640, 1641 : as also, 1681 are most faithfully and impartially examined, collected, and compared together for the present seasonable use, benefit and information of the publick : as also the wonderful and most solemn manner and form of ratifying, confirming and pronouncing of that most dreadful curse and execration against the violators and infringers of Magna Charta in the time of Henry the Third, King of England, &amp;c. ... / by Theophilus Rationalis ...</title>
                  <author>Rationalis, Theophilus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rich. Janeway ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Theophilus Rationalis is a pseudonym for Henry Duke. Author identified in no. 104 of the Observator.--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Stuarts, 1603-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59492:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M in PARVO, aut VOX VERITATIS:</hi> WHEREIN THE PRINCIPLES, PRACTICES, AND TRANSACTIONS OF THE Engliſh Nation: But more eſpecially and in particular BY THEIR Repreſentatives Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1640, 1641: As alſo 1680, 1681.</p>
            <p>ARE Moſt faithfully and impartially Examined, Collected, and Compared together for the preſent ſeaſonable Uſe, Benefit and Information of the Publick.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO, The Wonderful and moſt Solemn Manner and Form of Ratifying, Confirming and Pronouncing of that moſt dreadful Curſe and Execration againſt the Violaters and Infringers of <hi>MAGNA CHARTA</hi> in the Time of <hi>HENRY</hi> the Third, King of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>All which is earneſtly recommended to the moſt ſerious and impartial Conſideration, and peruſal of all His MAJESTIES moſt Loyal, and moſt Obedient Subjects (the true <hi>Tory, Phanatick,</hi> and <hi>Bloody Papiſt</hi> only excepted) within His Realms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions and Territories thereunto belonging.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> THEOPHILUS RATIONALIS, <hi>a Perſon of Quality, and a moſt true Lover of his King and Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Rich. Janeway,</hi> in <hi>Queens-head-Alley</hi> in <hi>Pater-noſter-Row.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59492:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59492:2"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle Dedicatory.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the KING'S moſt Excellent Majeſty, <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second, by the Grace of God, of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Proteſtant King, Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Dread Soveraign!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have preſumed to proſtrate the enſuing Lines at Your Majeſties feet, in regard you are the only Perſon in all your Three Kingdoms, that is moſt nearly and principally therein concerned. And I dare be bold to affirm (although they are very high, proud and lofty words), <hi>viz.</hi> That if Your Majeſty ſhall be pleaſed, without prejudice, prepoſſeſſion and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality, moſt ſolemnly and ſeriouſly to peruſe the ſame, and will be pleaſed to take your future meaſures accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly: I ſay then, I am very confident, and fully aſſured (unleſs I have no reaſon nor underſtanding remaining in me, but am delivered over into a reprobate ſenſe), That Your Majeſty may yet be (unleſs the Decree be already gone out againſt us for our total ruine and deſtruction) one of the greateſt and happieſt Monarchs
<pb facs="tcp:59492:3"/>this day in the Chriſtian World. <hi>Verbum ſapienti,</hi> &amp;c. I have done my duty, and have diſcharged my Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy unto your Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty (whom God long preſerve), and am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(GREAT SIR)</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſties moſt Loyal, moſt Obedient, and moſt Faithful Subject and Servant, to Love, Honour, and Serve You and my Countrey</hi> uſque ad Mortem. Theophilus Rationalis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:59492:3"/>
            <head>THE INTRODUCTION AUT <hi>LIBER ad LECTOREM.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>STand off proud Rebels: Royaliſts draw near,</l>
            <l>To ſee your Prince i'th' front, the Pope i'th' rear.</l>
            <l>Let not the Pope affright you, nor diſpoſe</l>
            <l>Your thoughts to wander after <hi>Charles</hi> his foes:</l>
            <l>The Center clears all doubts that ſhall ariſe</l>
            <l>From Helliſh Plotters, under a diſguiſe</l>
            <l>Of State-reformers; though at the ſelf-ſame time</l>
            <l>Both Church and State, their principal deſign</l>
            <l>Is for to ruine: But ſtill in Maſquerades,</l>
            <l>The Pope and Devil being chief Comrades</l>
            <l>Unto theſe Helliſh Monſters, who would bring</l>
            <l>Deſtruction to your Church, confuſion to your King.</l>
            <l>Heavens bleſs your Head, with ſuch as will now pleaſe</l>
            <l>To guard him from ſuch Sycophants as theſe;</l>
            <l>Who doubtleſs will, by their inveterate hate,</l>
            <l>At length prove ruine both to Church and State,</l>
            <l>If not prevented by Gods liberal hand,</l>
            <l>Under Great <hi>Charles,</hi> who hath the ſole Command</l>
            <l>And Power to ſave you, if he will but call</l>
            <l>His Council once again near to <hi>Whitehall,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And let them ſit for to diſpatch this Crew</l>
            <l>Of Wolves and Tygers; Then will ſtraight enſue</l>
            <l>A laſting Peace 'twixt Him and People both.</l>
            <l>I muſt conclude, to ſpeak the reſt I'm loth.</l>
            <l>This Book it ſelf will ſpeak enough, to bring</l>
            <l>Peace to the People, Honour to your King.</l>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:59492:4"/>
            <head>To all the truly Loyal-Hearted Nobility, Gentry, and Commonalty of this Land: The moſt grave, ſober, ſerious, and truly Religious People, and moſt faithful obedient Subjects unto his preſent Majeſty; though called by the Nick-names of Fanaticks, Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptiſts, Arminians, Socinians, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinarians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>ROwze Loyal <hi>Fannees,</hi> look well to your Guard,</l>
               <l>The bold <hi>God-damme</hi>'s are in your Rear-ward:</l>
               <l>Pray do not budg, keep cloſe within your Station,</l>
               <l>Theſe men of late have poiſon'd half the Nation</l>
               <l>With bloody Tenets under a diſguiſe,</l>
               <l>To make you Traitors, and a legal Prize</l>
               <l>The Soveraign Tree of <hi>Tyburn</hi> to advance,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Ketch</hi> their Foreman, muſt lead up the dance</l>
               <l>Call'd <hi>Towzer</hi>'s Mole-trap, and the Tories Gin,</l>
               <l>(Now have at all) to catch poor <hi>Fannees</hi> in.</l>
               <l>God help you now: They ſwear they will you kill,</l>
               <l>Becauſe of you they cannot have their will.</l>
               <l>You have (ſay they) diſturb'd both Church &amp; State,</l>
               <l>For which they love you with a mortal hate.</l>
               <l>And now they'l hang you t'rid themſelves from evil,</l>
               <l>And ſend you packing to <hi>Old Nick</hi> the Devil</l>
               <l>By ſome Sham-Plots. This is the only way</l>
               <l>To ſlay ſuch Rebels as have gone aſtray</l>
               <l>So long a time from their moſt holy Church,</l>
               <l>And now <hi>Old Nick</hi> ſhall leave them in the lurch.</l>
               <l>Damm them and Sink them all, they ſhall not live:</l>
               <l>There's not a man whom our Great <hi>Charles</hi> ſhall give</l>
               <l>To him his Life, If we may have our will,</l>
               <l>This is the time to uſe our utmoſt skill.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59492:4"/>
We'll tell Great <hi>Charles,</hi> that if he now ſhould ſpare</l>
               <l>But one of theſe, all his three Kingdoms are</l>
               <l>In danger to be loſt; and with this helliſh hook</l>
               <l>We'll catch the Fiſh, and then how will they look</l>
               <l>Like Sons of Whores, when <hi>Ketch</hi> ſhall them befool,</l>
               <l>And mount them up upon his three legg'd Stool?</l>
               <l>Courage, brave <hi>Towzers,</hi> Here's a noble Plot,</l>
               <l>Effect but this, the firſt will be forgot:</l>
               <l>Make King and Council both to underſtand,</l>
               <l>That damn'd Rogue <hi>Godfrey</hi> with his proper hand</l>
               <l>Did ſlay himſelf: Our work will then be done,</l>
               <l>And we ſhall ſhine like to the glorious Sun</l>
               <l>At his Meridian height; and ever after</l>
               <l>We'll break our Faſts with merriment and laughter,</l>
               <l>To ſee what Fools we made the Tory Crew,</l>
               <l>Who to the Plot did ſtraightway bid adieu.</l>
               <l>And ſwore to boot that we were innocent,</l>
               <l>Of all the Impeachments which the Parliament</l>
               <l>Did faſten on us, whom we have outdone,</l>
               <l>Although as guilty as our riſing Sun</l>
               <l>Will ſhew himſelf, when as he ſhall appear</l>
               <l>Before his Equals, to bring up the Rear</l>
               <l>Of all the Plots and Sham-Plots that have been</l>
               <l>Contriv'd by us er'e ſince his Coming in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here ſtop you Helhounds in your full career,</l>
               <l>Theſe Loyal <hi>Fanns</hi> will make you quake for fear.</l>
               <l>Their God above will ſurely them defend,</l>
               <l>And bring your Rogueſhips to your fatal end.</l>
               <l>Who then ſhall ſmile, and have you in deriſion,</l>
               <l>For all your Libels, and your late Miſpriſion</l>
               <l>Of Treaſon on them; from your bitter Gall,</l>
               <l>To make them Rebels to their Kings <hi>Whitehall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But hark!</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59492:5"/>
You ſhall be Summon'd 'fore the Council-Board</l>
               <l>Of the next Parliament, where a wiſe word</l>
               <l>We ſhall not hear from you, only Evaſions,</l>
               <l>Lyes, Shifts, and Stories, Mental reſervations,</l>
               <l>For to evade your guilt, which ſhall appear</l>
               <l>As clear as Cryſtal in our Hemiſphere.</l>
               <l>When as bright <hi>Sol</hi> ſhall mount his Royal Steed,</l>
               <l>To give us light, whereof we ſtand in need;</l>
               <l>Heavens ſay <hi>Amen</hi> now; If it be your will,</l>
               <l>When this is done, let Peace continue ſtill.</l>
               <l>This, oh dear Heavens, is now my plain requeſt,</l>
               <l>That ſo poor <hi>Fanns</hi> at length may have ſome reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Bellum dat litem dat pax bona quaeque Deorum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t tandem redeas, jain peritura preor.)</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I am, Right Honourable, Right Worſhipful, and well-belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Commoners, Your moſt Humble, moſt Faithful, and moſt Obedient Servant to be commanded,</hi> Theophilus Rationalis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59492:5"/>
            <head>Multum in Parvo, AUT <hi>VOX VERITATIS,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THAT we are fallen into an Age wherein almoſt all ſorts of Men amongſt us are ſtill ſetled upon their Lees, there's none of us all ſo happy as to be ignorant thereof; and how that the Judgments and Sentiments of Men (and more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in this latter Age of the World) are moſt ſtrangely degenerated, biaſſed, enſlaved, and almoſt overwhelmed with pride, vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, hypocriſie, ſelf-intereſt (that great <hi>Diana</hi> and Goddeſs of this World), ambition, paſſion, prejudice, partiality, faction, rebellion, the eſpouſing of a party, <hi>Et cum multis aliis,</hi> &amp;c. And yet that which is moſt wonderful, and matter of aſtoniſhment, is this, <hi>viz.</hi> That all theſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in general, or particular, do declare and pretend, That as to their ſeveral Tranſactions in the World, wherein they are concerned, and in oppoſition to the reſt of their Neighbours, is purely to manifeſt their great and fervent Zeal to the Honour and Glory of Almighty God, and to promote (as much as in them lyes) a moſt firm; exact, and uniform Obedience (not omitting at all times their ſpecious pretences of their ſteady and untainted Loyalty to their Prince) both in Church and State.</p>
            <p>But how theſe Gentlemen, and ſpecious Pretenders before mentioned; will come off at the long run (for as we uſually ſay, <hi>Finis coronat opns</hi>) without a ſcratch't face, and a blot in their ſcutcheons, when-as their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Tranſactions ſhall be impartially examined and ſearched to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, is a kind of a pretty queſtion to be ſtarted; and indeed it would be a very ingenious and pleaſant divertiſement to any perſon that would make it his buſineſs to ſtudy the point, and thoroughly and impartially to make an experiment thereof.</p>
            <p>This ſmall Treatiſe (Courteous Readers) peradventure may give you ſome ſmall ſatisfaction, in relation to the premiſes; and it is more than probable, that others hereafter of a more learned and more ingenious ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, may take example by this ſmall and well-intended piece to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large thereupon, and farther to explain what I have here ſuccinctly inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated only for my own, and for ſome others (which I ſhall forbear to name) preſent and ſeaſonable ſatisfaction, as to thoſe grand Debates, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels and Tranſactions which are now in the midſt of us upon the wheel, (and here I muſt beg, that the Lord of his infinite Grace and Mercy would
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59492:6"/>be pleaſed to ſend us at length a good iſſue upon them all) both in Church and State.</p>
            <p>This I thought requiſite to cite by way of Introduction, and now will take leave to conduct you ſomewhat cloſer and nearer to our matter in hand, <hi>Et honoi ſoit que mal y penſe</hi>); and herein we ſhall proceed in manner and form as followeth.</p>
            <p>That we are fallen at preſent, not only into a degenerate, rebellious, ambitious and ſtubborn Age; but in particular, into a very curious, cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, and obnoxious time in that age, <hi>viz. Anno Domini</hi> 1680, and 1681, wherein (as by experience is manifeſtly true) a man is almoſt made (though not in the edg of the Law, but in the edg of ſome others who would be Law-makers) a Capital offender for ſome words placing or ſpeaking, which peradventure may be very good, orthodox and loyal in themſelves, until they come to be ſcanned, weighed, and interpreted by others in a quite different and contrary ſenſe. (I know, Courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, you are moſt of you, at leaſt the beſt of you, able, and I hope wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to joyn iſſue with me herein, as Atteſtators to the truth hereof).</p>
            <p>But whether there be a fatality in theſe preſent years, as there was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 40 years ſince, which are by-paſt and gone, and all things buried (or at leaſt ought to be forgotten) in an Act of Oblivion as to the Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe (as we do uſually call them) rebellious times; or whether this critical time doth portend good things to his Majeſty of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein</hi>'s (whom God of his infinite mercy long preſerve for our peace and quietneſs ſake) affairs and concerns as to his preſent Government in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; or whether of any good conſequence to the Subjects of his Three Kingdoms in general; or whether this year the Lyon and the Lamb ſhall not lye down together (according to an ancient Prophecy); or whether His Majeſties juſt Prerogative, and his Subjects Priviledges ſhall go hand in hand together, I am not able to determine (although ſome pretend to give a ſhrewd gueſs thereunto as to future contingencies), yet I will hope the beſt, as being fully perſwaded and convinced, that the God and Father of our bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Author of Peace, and Lover of Concord; and of the Souls of them who are willing under their Magiſtrates (whether Heathen or Chriſtian) to live quiet and peaceable lives in all godlineſs and honeſty, will be pleaſed at length to bring forth peace, tranquillity, and order, out of all our diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, animoſities and preſent confuſions. And herein let every true and Loyal-hearted Subject and Engliſh man ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, however, this I am ſure of (as being able to atteſt that truth in particular), <hi>viz.</hi> That humble Petitions and Addreſſes to His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> this year <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1681, is <hi>A-la-mode,</hi> and the very neweſt faſhion (and in my ſlender judgment and apprehenſion, is a very comely, decent, and commendable faſhion) ſince the Diſſolution of the late Parliament at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and His Majeſties late Declaration to all his Loving Subjects, and Ordered to be read (by the Reverend Clergy of the Land) in all Churches and Chappels; ſince which time Addreſſes and Humble Petitions have ſwarm'd in a main, from all Points of the compaſs (<hi>viz.</hi> from Cities, Burroughs, Towns-Corporate, Lieutenancies, Trained-Bands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) as if they were reſolved to ſtorm <hi>VVhitehall, VVind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor-Caſtle, Hampton-Court,</hi> and His Majeſty Himſelf (God of Heaven pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59492:6"/>Him), with no other weapons than ſteady and untainted Loyalty, and with all dutiful and humble Allegiance unto His Majeſties Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it is now by Law eſtabliſhed both in Church and State: And for the which the Lord High Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in the Perſon of His Majeſty, hath given them all his true and hearty Thanks for their ſo numerous and ſeaſonable appearing at this preſent conjuncture, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to ſome others, who, it ſeems, have not the good-hap with the reſt of their Neighbours (ſure it was by the malevolent aſpect and influence of ſome auſpicious male-contented Planets), to form and word their Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Addreſſes and Petitions according to the pattern in the <hi>Mount;</hi> and of theſe Loyal perſons that had been of the forlorn hope, and had marched in the front of the battel, and being weighed in the ballance of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary (I do not, neither dare I ſay, in the ballance of the Scriptures and right reaſon), they were found too light, and for the which they have a mark and a ſtamp put upon them by way of diſtinction (I had almoſt ſaid like unto that, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.15, 16, 17.) whereby they are branded and ſtigmatized as factious and diſloyal Subjects <hi>(Sed affirmatis eſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare),</hi> and are therefore regiſtred and recorded to be conveyed down by the Pens Militant to future poſterity, as perſons diſloyal and diſaffected to the preſent Government, and to all thoſe Noble Emoluments and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges which our Forefathers never yet ſaw, nor did enjoy (as ſome of the Addreſſes do moſt happily and emphatically word it) in ſo plentiful a meaſure, as under the preſent Reign of His moſt Sacred Majeſty (whom God long preſerve). The which I muſt needs ſay is a very hard caſe to thoſe poor Petitioners, and many of them good Gentlemen, able Citizens, and Perſons of Quality, who peradventure did all mean well, though their luck was bad; and therefore all the comfort that I can give them in this particular (in regard <hi>Solamen miſeriis</hi> is a very acceptable compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion), is only this, That they would be pleaſed to conſider, That if their hearts and hands went together, and had no baſe, nor rebellious, nor fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious deſign therein whatſoever; and that they were conſcious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they did their King and Country good ſervice in their late Humble Addreſſes and Petitions (although miſconſtrued and miſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted); That our bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, when he was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth (although the beſt perſon that ever breathed in the common air), yet he could not eſcape reflections and hard cenſures from his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen the <hi>Jews,</hi> upon the like account: For ſome of them ſaid (and but a few, God knows, in compariſon of the whole Nation) that he was a good man, when others of a more diſſolute and looſe converſation ſaid, Nay, but he was a Mountebank, and an Impoſtor, and deceived the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; therefore what ſhall we ſay to all things, but only
<q>Monſtrum horrendum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But to proceed, and come yet a little nearer unto the matter in hand, according to the Contents of the Title-page, <hi>viz.</hi> moſt faithfully and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially to examine and compare together the Principles, Practices and Tranſactions of the Engliſh Nation (but more eſpecially by their Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives Aſſembled in Parliament) <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1640, and 1641. and <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1680, and 1681. (The compleat and exact diſtance of time
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59492:7"/>the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the peculiar People of God, were wandring, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling and provoking his Divine Majeſty in the Wilderneſs, before they were actually poſſeſſed of the land of <hi>Canaan</hi>): And wherein perſons and things do now look and repreſent themſelves almoſt with the very ſame face (nay I had almoſt ſaid with a Ten-times more ominous, ill-featured, and diſmal aſpect than formerly). But yet notwithſtanding I can by no means apprehend the ſame dreadful fate and conſequence will enſue now, as did <hi>de facto</hi> in thoſe preceding years (<hi>viz.</hi> a Nation wading and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing over head and ears in hot Chriſtian blood, and ſheathing the naked ſword in each others bowels, and appealing to Law of Arms to decide the grand Controverſie in thoſe days, which ſo unfortunately hapned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Commons of <hi>England</hi> Aſſembled in Parliament, and his late Majeſty of deplorable Memory, the chief Magiſtrate thereof), although the true Phanatick, Tory and Tantivy-men of the Age, both in Preſs and Pulpit, do endeavour Might and Main (and leave no ſtone unturn'd in order thereunto) to poſſeſs our Governours, and thoſe that ſit at the Helm, with this vain, frivolous, and (I hope) ridiculous belief. But, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God, there are yet ſome few Wiſe men among us, who are of the contrary perſwaſion, and can penetrate as far into a Millſtone as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and who underſtand their black deſigns and meanings herein well enough (and how that they would willingly, and with all their hearts and ſouls be warming themſelves at ſuch a fire): And there is a juſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God above, who will at the laſt (as he hath in ſome good meaſure done already) countermine, bring to light, deſtroy and confound all their Plots and Sham-plots of this and the like nature whatſoever, and will make them to be rendred in his own good time, the very off-ſcum, ſcorn, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and deriſion of our Engliſh <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſhall be handled and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated down to future poſterity as the firebrands and principal fomentors of all our animoſities and unhappy diviſions.</p>
            <p>And here to come to a right underſtanding of thoſe precedent Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, we muſt make a Digreſſion, and by a retrograde ſtep take a tranſient view of the many Precurſors of our late unhappy Troubles and Revolutions, and which were engendring and fomenting in the Body Politique from the time of the Death of King <hi>James,</hi> until the beginning of thoſe years, wherein by reaſon of a Long, long, long Interval of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liements (or rather as ſome would have it, a long <hi>interregnum</hi> of two vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal parts of the Conſtitution it ſelf) our Engliſh Monarchy (although the beſt and well-temper'd Government, when the exerciſe of the vital parts thereof be not obſtructed in its due circulation, this day in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World) received for ſome time among us its Mortal wound.</p>
            <p>And herein, as I would not for my right hand vindicate or juſtifie any Illegal, Unwarrantable, or any Tyrannical Proceedings of any particular Number, or numbers of men whatſoever, and who were actually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in thoſe late, moſt diſmal, and moſt deplorable revolutions; ſo, on the other ſide, I would not altogether condemn all them who were then in the Vogue of the people, the eſteemed Patriots of their Lives, Liberties, and Properties, and the grand Aſſertors of the Kings Majeſties moſt Legal and Juſt Prerogatives both in Church and State; and thoſe that are yet <hi>inter vivos</hi> of them, do moſt ſolemnly proteſt and declare, That in proceſs of time, Perſons and Tranſactions were ſtretched forth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59492:7"/>to preternatural Dimenſions, and Diametrically oppoſite to the primary intentions and inclinations of the Houſe of Commons themſelves; and His preſent Majeſty that now Reigneth (whom God long preſerve in the midſt of us) was pleaſed from <hi>Breda</hi> moſt graciouſly to obſerve, <hi>viz.</hi> That through miſtakes and miſunderſtandings, many inconveniencies were produced, which were not intended. And that the <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> ſo called (although there hath been a much longer ſince) had no deſign in the leaſt meaſure in their primary thoughts and intentions to ſhake off the Monarchy (although there are ſome particular men at this preſent conjuncture of time in the Pulpit that make them to be all King <hi>Ahab</hi>'s, and that <hi>Naboth</hi>'s Vineyard and Inheritance was their principal deſign, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſlily couched under the ſpecious and godly pretence of Liberty and Property; wherein I think they are true Tory-men indeed, and very uncharitable in the higheſt meaſure), but only to prune and pare off ſome Luxuriant and overgrown branches (<hi>viz. Court Paraſites,</hi> evil Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, who were great Favorites, corrupt Judges, and ſuch-like Sycophants) which had well-nigh ſucked (like ſo many idle Drones) the very ſap from the root of our moſt Noble, Magnificent, thrice happy, and never enough to be admired Triple-Conſtitution.</p>
            <p>And in order to the accompliſhment of the aforementioned premiſes, I have conſulted ſeveral Authors for my beſt ſatisfaction, that are now extant, as to the Tranſactions of thoſe times, wherein, I muſt confeſs, I do find them at a very great diſtance and oppoſition one to another, and very various in their ſeveral ſentiments and apprehenſions, according to their particular inclinations as to the merit of the cauſe on either ſide; wherein, by the way (although with all due ſubmiſſion to the more grave, acurate and diſcerning Judgments of the Learned) I do humbly conceive, ſome of theſe have erred too much on the right, and others too much on the left hand; but yet as to matter of fact, as to what was really done and tranſacted in thoſe days, they do in the main generally all agree. And among the reſt I have peruſed one piece in particular, which in my ſlender apprehenſion hath avoided both extremes (and as we do uſually ſay, <hi>In Medio conſiſtet Virtus</hi>), and hath paſſed <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Charibdis</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any danger of too much reflecting upon either ſide: Him I have made choice of in particular, as one of the ableſt Pilates to ſteer my courſe through the Channel (whereby to avoid thoſe many Rocks and Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands which a man may ſuddenly run upon, if he have not the Conduct of an experienced guide), and ſo God ſend the good Ship of <hi>Vox Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas</hi> unto her deſired harbour; A Ship, though but ſmall in bulk, yet pretty handſomely and tight built for Publick ſervice, and I hope will be able ſtoutly to defend His Majeſties particular Perſon and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by King, Lords and Commons, againſt all bold Aſſaſſinates, againſt all crafty Incendiaries, againſt all curſed <hi>Achitophels,</hi> againſt all abſolute Monarchical Tories and Tantivies, againſt all Blood-thirſty and Helliſh Papiſts whatſoever, who would not only pervert, but utterly deſtroy the preſent beſt eſtabliſhed Government this day in the Chriſtian World, by ſtretching of it forth beyond its legal and due bounds, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo's, reſtrictions and limitations. And from ſuch notorious and malicious perſons in grain, let every good and loyal Subject, and every true En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh-man inſert it in his Quoditian Litany and private Devotion, <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:59492:8"/>
The Title of that particular piece I have even now mentioned is, <hi>viz. The Reign of King Charles:</hi> By <hi>H. L.</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>F. L.</hi> and <hi>J .G.</hi> for <hi>Henry Seile,</hi> Senior and Junior, over-againſt St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet;</hi> and <hi>Edward Dod</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> in <hi>Ivy-Lane,</hi> Anno Domini 1656.</p>
            <p>And that the ſaid perſon was not biaſſed, you may perceive by the Date thereof: It was in the time when the late Tyrant <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> had aſſumed the ſeat of chief Magiſtrate; and at that time of day to have dipped his Pen in gall, might have been very grateful and compleſant to that grand Uſurper, who having ſuch a puiſſant and dreadful Army of well-diſciplin'd, victorious and well-paid <hi>Janizaries</hi> at his Command, made the Lyon ſo impudently bold, as to call our grand Charter of <hi>England, Magna Charta, Magna F.</hi>—And in a ſmall ſpace of time after that, it pleaſed God to ſnatch him away from us in a high tempeſtuous wind, as an example to all future Tyrants who ſhall offer to attempt the like bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon our fundamental Laws, Liberties and Properties.</p>
            <p>And that you may be the better ſatisfied as to the impartiality of this ingenious and fair Hiſtorian (what he was, or is, if as yet <hi>inter vivos,</hi> I cannot tell), Pray do but peruſe his Preface to the ſaid Hiſtory, and you will find <hi>in his Verbis,</hi> in his own Apology, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Oblique Deſcants will come to Traverſe upon this honeſt Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, I already prejudicate. The fate of thoſe who write of Times within ken, Time's better for the Hiſtory, than for the Hiſtorian.</p>
            <p>For while they render truth more reſplendent, they uſually bring the Relator under a cloud, whence the bane of all faithful Tradition, that an Hiſtorian is rarely found, until the truth be loſt: And what is Hiſtory without its Idium? Truth, but a meer Romance: And if ſo, what Pen will undertake the Hiſtory of a King? Kings in their Functions ſo nearly reſemble the Divine Nature, as God himſelf hath ſtiled them Gods. And as in many reſpects they repreſent it, ſo alſo in that of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> though not in his ſenſe, <hi>De Deo etiam periculoſum eſt dicere verum.</hi> Though as man they are within the incidence of frailty (for as that Emperor ſaid, <hi>Imperium non tollit affectus,</hi> Soveraignty doth not proſcribe humane affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions), yet their failings have been in former times accounted like their Perſons, ſo ſacred, that to touch them, though never ſo tenderly, hath been eſteemed Petty-Treaſon: But in King <hi>Charles</hi> (the grand concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe Annals) the danger is counter-changed, and to exhibit in him any thing of merit and importance leſs than a <hi>Nero</hi> or <hi>Domitian,</hi> many will not endure. And theſe two extremes make my paſſage through this Hiſtory, like that of <hi>Jonathans</hi> to the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> a ſharp Rock on the one ſide, and a ſharp Rock on the other ſide. Which conſideration hath moved me to decline many things, otherwiſe remarkable, and not commonly known, and to content my ſelf with ſaving truths; nor ſhould I have adventured a modeſt Vindication of this King in ſome particulars, (not reflecting upon the fatal proceedings againſt him) had not the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity of ſome eminently diſaffected to him led me the way.</p>
            <p>But if in relation to theſe perils I have been ſtudious to bear my ſelf erect, yet in other concernments ſome will cenſure me for too ſtrong a Biaſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59492:8"/>
Some will ſay, peradventure, I ſeem no friend to the Clergy; and leſt my ſilence ſhould make this an Accuſation, which is but a meer Calumny, I anſwer, Churchmen I honour (no man more), and this I do for their Sacred Orders ſake: But if their Order be Sacred, it doth not (I wiſh it did) make all ſuch who are initiated in that Order; too many of that holy profeſſion are, ever were, and will be Sacred in another, and worſe ſenſe.</p>
            <p>The unſanctified lives of ſome officiating at the Sacred Altar, have been the complaint of all ages. Read we not (to their ſhame) of the ſons of <hi>Eli,</hi> whoſe impiety made them abhor the Offerings of the Lord? Doth not <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> tell us of ſome of his Contemporaries, who, had Canonical Diſcipline, been punctually obſerved, ſhould not have been permitted ſo much as to ſtep over the threſhold of Gods houſe, were notwithſtanding advanced to the higheſt griſon of Church-Dignities?</p>
            <p>And if this Narrative preſents ſome <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> blame-worthy, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is fallacious, that therefore our times are worſe than former, or that the accrimination overſpreadeth all: No, what St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid of ſome <hi>Enormitans</hi> in his time, is no leſs true of ours; That though our Church had cauſe to grieve for the blemiſhes of ſome, yet might ſhe glory in the Ornaments of more.</p>
            <p>And ſo much ſhall ſerve for my preſent purpoſe as to the former part of this Authors Preface,<note place="margin">Et ſi conſtriſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur de aliqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis tamen conſolamur de pluribus Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis. <hi>Aug. Epiſt. 137.</hi>
               </note> wherein he doth endeavour to ſatisfie his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that he will carry an even hand between either ſide, and ſteer his courſe aright; and ſo far I ſhall endeavour (as much as in me lyes) to write after his Copy: But yet where perſons are blame-worthy, I ſhall not be Meal-mouth'd, but let them know their failings and embecilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, until they give me better ſatisfaction than I have at preſent concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Reformation.</p>
            <p>And now to tranſcribe ſome of this Authors Narrative, concerning the <hi>Reign of King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt;</hi> ſo wiſe, ſo vertuous, ſo temperate, ſo chaſte, ſo learned, and ſo religious a Prince, and a ſtrong aſſertor of the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt the Old Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at <hi>Rome,</hi> and all his adherents; yet that this Prince after his Death by the Pens-Militant, inſtead of inſerting this Parentheſis concerning him, (as they have done of many Princes after their deceaſe) of <hi>Ever bleſſed Memory,</hi> ſhould be conſtrained to counterchange their Dialect, and ſay of <hi>Ever unfortunate and deplorable Memory;</hi> I muſt confeſs is ſo profound a myſtery unto me, that I am not able to ſearch and penetrate into the depth thereof, and therefore muſt leave this (I could wiſh I were not able to ſay ſo much by experience) moſt unfortunate Prince (though of <hi>Ever bleſſed Memory</hi> in ſome ſenſe) unto the ſearcher of all hearts (and before whom all things are naked, bare and open), who worketh, and wiſely diſpoſeth of all things both in Heaven and in Earth, according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible and moſt unerring Councel and Dictates of his own Will.</p>
            <p>But to proceed in my intended deſign, to Tranſcribe from my Author ſome of the particular and moſt material Tranſactions as to matter of fact in thoſe days (and ſhould I have tranſcribed the whole, it would have been a new Edition of the ſaid Narrative, and would have ſwelled this ſmall piece (which was intended for no other in my primary cogitations) unto a very large Bulk, the which you may pleaſe to peruſe in manner and form as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59492:9"/>
King <hi>James</hi> ſurrendred his Soul to God (and his Three Kingdoms to his Son) at <hi>Theobalds,</hi> Anno Domini, <hi>March</hi> the <hi>27th,</hi> 1625.</p>
            <p>And now it will not be amiſs (ſaith the ingenious Hiſtorian) nor vary from the uſual ceremony ordained to the body of extinct Princes, if I here repreſent in brief the pourtraicture of this Famous Monarch, which I will do freely, ſincerely, and with a ſpirit which equally diſdains to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel or flatter him.</p>
            <p>In the ſtile of the Court,<note place="margin">His Character.</note> he went for <hi>Great Britains Solomon;</hi> nor is it any excurſion beyond the Precincts of verity, to ſay, that neither <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> nor any other Kingdom whatſoever could ever ſince <hi>Solomon</hi>'s days glory in a King (for recondite learning and abſtruſe knowledge), ſo near a match to <hi>Solomon</hi> as he: And though he was a Univerſal Scholar, yet did he make other Sciences (their moſt proper imployment), but drudges and ſervitors to Divinity, wherein he became ſo tranſcendently eminent, as he notoriouſly foil'd the greateſt Clerks of the <hi>Roman</hi> See: Nor did his Theological abilities more advantage the Cauſe of Religion abroad, than at home, they keeping the new-fangled Clergy aloof, and at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as not daring to infuſe into ſo ſolid a judgment their upſtart and erroneous fancies, no nor diſquiet the Churches peace with Heterodox opinions (by which it appears this Author and King <hi>James</hi> were both <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> as to their particular Sentiments in matters of Religion); A ſtout adverſary he was to the <hi>Arminians</hi> and <hi>Semi-Pelagians,</hi> whom he called as <hi>Proſper</hi> before him (and ſo doth the whole tribe of them ever ſince) the Enemies of Gods grace.</p>
            <p>And as ſlender a friend he was to the Presbytery (here he intends in matters Eccleſiaſtical, as to the form of Church-government and impoſed Conſtitutions), of whoſe Tyrannical and Antimonarchical principles he had from his cradle ſmart experience; He was an excellent Speaker, the Scheme of his Oratory being more ſtately than Pedantick, and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions argued him both a King and Scholar: In his apparel and civil garb he ſeemed naturally to affect a Majeſtick careleſneſs, which was ſo hectick and habitual in him, as even in Religious exerciſes (where the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal demeanor is a grand part of that ſacred homage) he was ſomewhat too incurious and irreverent: He was indulgent a little to his Palat, and had a ſmack of the Epicure: In pecuniary diſpenſations to his Favourites he was moſt exceſſive liberal, yea though the exigence of his own wants pleaded retention: Nor was <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf more a <hi>Solomon,</hi> according to the true notion of the word, which imports a man of reſt, than he, ſelecting for his Motto, <hi>Beati Pacifici,</hi> or the ſeventh Beatitude, as moſt agreeable to his genius and natural conſtitution; He was ſtudious of peace ſomewhat over-much for a King; in purſuit whereof, Virtue flew to a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſening, and (in the opinion of many) out of ſight, he incurring thereby the note of Puſillanimity, very ſuſpicious from his managing the Cauſe of the <hi>Palatinate;</hi> for had not the thought of War been terrible unto him, would he ſo long have endured his Son-in-law, exterminated from his Patrimony, while the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Faction (to his great diſhonour) cajol'd, and kept him in deluſory chat with ſpecious fallacies? Would he in thoſe feveral Negotiations of <hi>Carliſle, Briſtow, Belfaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſton,</hi> have ſpent ſo vaſt ſums, the moity whereof, had they been diſpoſed in Military-levies and preparations, would have Modell'd an Army able (when <hi>Hidleburgh,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59492:9"/>Manhrein</hi> and <hi>Frankindale</hi> defended themſelves) to have totally diſſipated all the forces of the Uſurpers, to have Maſter'd the imperious Eagle, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing her to forego her Quary, and reinſtate the <hi>Paulſgrave?</hi> Would he ſo tediouſly have courted the Alliance of <hi>Spain,</hi> to the very great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret of his Subjects, whom his Predeceſſor had ſo often baffled, and whom <hi>England</hi> ever found a worſe friend than enemy? What ſtronger Evidence can be given in of a wonderful defect of courage?</p>
            <p>As this faint-heartedneſs loſt him the reputation and reſpects of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſo his heavy preſſures upon them, and undue Levies by Privy-Seals, and the like, alienated their affections, eſpecially conſidering how thoſe Moneys were miſemployed, indeed rather thrown away, partly in the two diſhonourable Treaties of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and the conſequential En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments, and partly in Largeſſes upon his Minion <hi>Buckingham.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this diſaffection and contempt in his People, there was generated a general diſpoſition to turbulent and boiſterous darings, and expoſtulations even againſt his darling Prerogative. And though thoſe diſmal calamities which after befel his Son, were ampliated doubtleſs by a ſuperfetation of cauſes, yet was their firſt and main exiſtency derivative from thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited grounds: Let Court-Pens extol the calmneſs of his Halcion Reign with all the artifice of Rhetorick: Let them conclude the Parable, and tell us, God gave King <hi>James</hi> alſo as he did <hi>Solomon,</hi> reſt from all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies round about; yet can they never truly deny, but that admired ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity had its ſet in a cloud, and that he left to his Succeſſor a Crown of Thorns, as being engaged to contend with two puiſſant Enemies: Firſt the mighty Monarch of the Weſt, the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> Secondly the more invincible of the two, an empty purſe; For that King who hath this Enemy to encounter, ſhall never archieve any thing of glorious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.</p>
            <p>The death of this Famous Monarch cauſed no other <hi>interregnum,</hi> than of joy, his Son <hi>Charles</hi> being immediately by Sir <hi>Edward Zouch</hi> (then Knight Marſhal) proclaimed at the Court-gate, King of <hi>Great Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> His firſt Act of Regality was to diſpatch Aviſo's of his Fathers deceaſe to Foreign Princes and States, his Correſpondents, with whom he was in Amity. Next, he took into care the becoming Obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies of the Royal Corps, which removed from <hi>Theobalds</hi> to <hi>Denmark-houſe</hi> in <hi>London, April</hi> the <hi>23d,</hi> was thence, the <hi>7th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> conveyed to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and there inhum'd with the greateſt Solemnities, and moſt ſtately Ritualities could be deviſed.</p>
            <p>Though grief had taken up the principal Lodgings of King <hi>Charles</hi> his heart, yet did it not quite turn love out of doors: but he had ſtill an eye to <hi>France,</hi> and held himſelf concern'd to let his Agents know he was mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the ſtock he had going there; and to rear a firm aſſurance of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious intentions, He ſent over Letters of Procuration for the Duke of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereux</hi> to eſpouſe the Lady <hi>Henrietta Maria;</hi> only he added this eſpecial precaution, That thoſe Letters ſhould not be reſigned up until <hi>May</hi> the <hi>8th,</hi> when the Celebrities of his Fathers Funeral would be over; for he would not that grief and joy (things incompatible) ſhould juſtle. But theſe inſtructions (for what cauſe I know not) were not in all points preciſely obſerved: for on <hi>May</hi> the <hi>11th,</hi> as others; and the firſt, as we compute, ſix days before King <hi>James</hi> his Obſequies, the Eſpouſals were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59492:10"/>ſolemnized in the Church of <hi>Noſtredame</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> the Queen being given by her two Brothers, the King and Monſieur; the Nuptials paſt, the Royal Bride prepared for <hi>England;</hi> and to wait upon her with the greater ſplendor, his Majeſty diſpatcheth over the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> with the Earl of <hi>Montgomery,</hi> and other Perſons of Quality. <hi>May</hi> the <hi>24th</hi> they arrived at <hi>Paris,</hi> and <hi>June</hi> the <hi>2d</hi> the Queen (after the iteration of moſt affectionate adieux reciprocated and interchanged between the King and her ſelf), ſet forward for <hi>Amiens;</hi> where being attended with a moſt Princely retinue, ſhe was under the reſtraint of a Magnificent Entertainment till the 16 of that Month; thence ſhe diſ-lodged for <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loigne,</hi> where ſhe was to Embarque for <hi>England</hi> (the Contagion then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much at <hi>Calais</hi>); there ſhe found ready to receive her 21 tall Ships ſent from her deareſt, with a gallant Convoy of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham,</hi> and other Ladies of Honour and Eminence to ſerve her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the <hi>22d</hi> ſhe ſet Sail for <hi>England,</hi> and Landed ſafe at <hi>Dover,</hi> after a turbulent and tempeſtuous paſſage. His Majeſty lay that night at <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> and next morning with joy incredible greeted his Royal Conſort, and conducted her to <hi>Canterbury,</hi> where the Marriage was finally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated; the Duke of <hi>Chevereux,</hi> his Majeſties former Repreſentative, conſigning up his precious charge to the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have heard ſome who undertake to mate all events with their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cauſes, paſſionately aſcribe <hi>Englands</hi> Calamities to thoſe Internuptials, and fetch that ireful ſtroke of Divine vengeance upon his late Majeſty, from his Marrying a Lady of miſ-belief.</p>
            <p>Grant I do, that both <hi>England</hi>'s and his Majeſties Sufferings may (in ſome ſort) be reductive to the caſualty of that Match; but that there was any intrinſick noxiouſneſs in it, either as <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Popiſh,</hi> I am not yet convinced.</p>
            <p>The ſame time, while His Majeſty was thus buſied in his Amorous Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation abroad, he plyed as well his Intereſt at home; and while he Wooed his Royal Miſtriſs there, he made Love to his People here, by Summoning a Parliament; that League being not more important to him as Man, than this as King; for as Man is without a female Conſort, ſo is a King without his Supreme Council, an half-form'd ſteril thing; the natural Extracts of the one, procreated without a Wife, are not more ſpurious than the Laws, the politick Deſcendents of the other, without was commenced at <hi>VVeſtminſter, June</hi> the <hi>18th.</hi> At firſt interview it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared under the ſcheme and faſhion of a Money-Wedding, and, in truth, the publick affairs did then implore no leſs. Upon the opening the Parliament, the King imparted his mind to the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to this effect.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59492:10"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOU are not ignorant, that at your earneſt intreaty, <hi>March 23. 1623,</hi> my Father (of happy Memory) firſt took up Arms for the recovery of the <hi>Palatinate;</hi> for which purpoſe, by your aſſiſtance, he began to form a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Army, and to prepare a goodly <hi>Armado</hi> and <hi>Navy-Royal:</hi> But death intervening between him and the atchievement, the War with the Crown is devolved upon me. To the proſecution whereof, as I am obliged both in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Honour, ſo I queſtion not but the ſame neceſſity continuing, you will cheriſh the action with the like affection, and farther it with a ready con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution. True it is, you furniſhed my Father with affectionate ſupplies, but they held no ſymmetry or proportion with the charge of ſo great an enterprize, for thoſe your Donatives are all disburs'd to a penny; and I am enforced to ſummon you hither, to tell you, That neither can the Army advance, nor the Fleet ſet forth without your aid.</p>
                  <p>Conſider, I pray you, the Eyes of all <hi>Europe</hi> are defixt upon me, to whom I ſhall appear ridiculous, as though I were unable to out-go Muſter and Oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, if you now deſert me; it is my firſt attempt, wherein, if I ſuſtain a foil, it will blemiſh all my future Honour.</p>
                  <p>If mine cannot, let your Reputations move, deliver and expedite me fairly out of this War, wherewith you have becumbred (let it never be ſaid wherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into you have betrayed) me. I deſire therefore your ſpeedy ſupply; ſpeedy I call it, for elſe it will prove no ſupply. The Sun you know is entring into his declining point; ſo it will be ſoon too late to ſet forth, when it will be rather not too ſoon to return. Again, I muſt mind you of the Mortality now Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in this City, which ſhould it (and ſo it may, and no breach of priviledge neither) arreſt any one Member of either Houſe, it ſoon would put a period both to Conſultation and Seſſion, ſo that your own periclitation neceſſitates an early reſolution.</p>
                  <p>In ſum, three of the beſt Rhetoricians, Honour, Opportunity and Safety, are all of a plot, and plead, you ſee, for expedition. Perhaps it may be expected I ſhould ſay ſomething in way of Account of my Religion, as alſo of the Temper and Tenure of my future Government. But as I hope I have not been guilty of any thing which may juſtly ſtart the leaſt queſtion in either, ſo I would deſire you to repoſe in this aſſurance, That I will in neither vary from thoſe principles, wherein I have been inſtituted at the feet of that Eminent <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> my late Father.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Speech being ended, the King Vailed his Crown, a thing rare in any of his Predeceſſors.</p>
            <p>Though denied it could not be, but this Speech was elemented of very rational materials, and ponderous arguments; yet it did not cauſe ſuch a precipitation of reſolution, but that the Parliament did deſcend to the conſideration thereof by degrees.</p>
            <p>That which retarded the Debate, was this: They had in ſtore by them two Petitions; one for Religion, the other againſt Grievances; to which having been moulded in King <hi>James</hi> his time, and preferr'd to him at the cloſe of the laſt Seſſions of the laſt Parliament, they (as yet) never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived anſwer. They ſaid it was the ancient, and as they conceived, a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59492:11"/>moſt prudential practice, to preſent Petitions at the Commencement of Parliaments; or ſo long before their Diſſolutions, as the King might have time to return a deliberate Anſwer; That the ſame courſe they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved ſtrictly to purſue, and give priority of diſpatch to thoſe Petitions, before any other buſineſs whatſoever; which accordingly they did.</p>
            <p>To the ſeveral Heads againſt Grievances, His Majeſty gave a diſtinct and ſatisfactory anſwer, and promiſed largely upon the Petition for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and the better to draw on Supplies, he did <hi>audit</hi> unto them the ſeveral Disburſements, both relating to the Army and Navy, that ſo all jealouſies of miſ-employment might be removed; which produced ſo good effects, as that the Laity gave him freely, and without condition, two Subſidies from Proteſtants, and four from Papiſts, as a mulct from the Houſe upon their Recuſancy, and the Clergy three.</p>
            <p>This was upon <hi>July</hi> the <hi>8th;</hi> and the next day the King ſignified, That he took notice of the ſlender appearance in the Houſe, by reaſon of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion; and that therefore having a tender regard to their healths, he declared his intention of Adjournig them upon <hi>Monday</hi> next, being the <hi>11th</hi> of that Month, which accordingly was performed to the <hi>1ſt</hi> of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> and <hi>Oxford</hi> named for the place, which gave diſguſt to ſome Members of the Houſe.</p>
            <p>In this Seſſions of Parliament was Mr. <hi>Montague</hi> queſtioned for Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing certain Books prejudicial to the Proteſtant Cauſe; for which he was ordered to be brought to the Bar; to whom the Speaker declared the pleaſure of the Houſe, That they would refer his Cenſure to the next Meeting; and in the interim, in reſpect of his notorious contempt, he ſhould ſtand committed to the Serjeants Ward, entring Bail for his then appearance.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Mountague</hi> had, by the cunning artifice of his Court-friends, crept into the Kings ſervice undiſcern'd; and the King ſignified to the Parliament two days after, That he thought his Servants (whereof <hi>Mountague</hi> was one) might have as much Protection as the Servant of an ordinary Burgeſs; nevertheleſs his Bond of 2000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> whereupon he was Bailed, continued uncancell'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>1ſt</hi> the Parliament met again at <hi>Oxford;</hi> the Divinity-School was appointed for the Houſe of Commons, and the Galleries above for the Houſe of Lords.</p>
            <p>The <hi>4th</hi> of the ſame Month, both Houſes were called together to <hi>Chriſt-Church-Hall</hi> by the King, where he laid open unto them his wants, for ſetting forth the Fleet; but the Parliament, before they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn any Anſwer, preſented him with a Petition againſt Recuſants, to this effect.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59492:11"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt Gracious Soveraign!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IT being infallibly true, that nothing can more eſtabliſh your Throne, and aſſure the peace and proſperity of your People, than the unity and ſincerity of Religion; We your Majeſties moſt humble and loyal Subjects, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, obſerving that of late there is an apparent, miſchievovs increaſe of Papiſts within your Dominions, hold our ſelves bound in conſcience and duty to preſent the ſame unto your Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, together with the dangerous conſequences, and what we conceive to be the moſt principal cauſes, and what may be the remedies thereof.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Their deſperate ends, being the Subverſion both of Church and State, and the reſtleſneſs of their ſpirits to attain thoſe ends, the Doctrines of their Teachers and Leaders perſwading them, that therein they ſhall do God good ſervice.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Their evident and ſtrict dependance upon ſuch Foreign Princes, as no way affect the good of your Majeſty and State.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> An opening a way of Popularity, to the ambition of any who ſhall adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to make himſelf Head of ſo great a party.</item>
                  </list>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The principal cauſes of the increaſe of Papiſts in thoſe times, and the remedies propoſed by the Parliament, I ſhall refer you to the Book it ſelf for your farther ſatisfaction. To all the ſeveral branches thereof the King, <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>7th,</hi> gave ſuch a plauſible and ſatisfactory anſwer, as nothing could be deſired more.</p>
            <p>One good turn, requires another: And as the King had given the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ample content by this Anſwer, ſo he hoped they would be as cheerful in ſupplying him with Moneys, for which he earneſtly impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tun'd them, and more eſpecially for his great Naval preparation; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon enſued a great Debate in the Houſe; ſome were very prompt to give, without delay; ſome would give, but in convenient time, but not then; others would give, but they complained that the deſign was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by young and ſingle Councel; that Sir <hi>Robert Manſell,</hi> a man of ſingular judgment and experience, had declared againſt the Plot, and had tender'd to the Council of War a project of much greater advantage, and leſs expence, which was approved by the Lord of <hi>Chicheſter;</hi> to the which the Solicitor replied in the Dukes behalf, That the Council of War (for the generality) much diſliked the project of Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> and concluded upon what was then intended; but the greater part agreed not to give, and to make an humble Remonſtrance, declaring the Cauſes and Reaſons of their not giving.</p>
            <p>Moſt of the Voters of this Remonſtrance flew high, and impetuouſly preſt in upon the Duke; ſome would diveſt him of his Offices, the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miralty eſpecially; others of his Revenue, by reſuming what he poſſeſt of the Crown-demeans; others demanded an account of what publick Moneys he had been entruſted with. This being ſignified to the King, he ſoon prognoſticated of what quality the Remonſtrance would prove; therefore immediately in diſtaſte, he determined to Diſſolve the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59492:12"/>
The Houſe of Commons were Reſolved into a Grand Committee, when the Uſher came from the Lords Houſe with that Meſſage; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would permit the Solicitor then in the Chair, to leave his ſeat, they agreed upon a Proteſtation, which Mr. <hi>Glanvill</hi> ſtood up and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to this effect.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>To give his Majeſty Thanks for his Gracious Anſwer to our Petition for Religion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Next, <hi>For his care of our health, in giving us leave to depart this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous time.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Laſtly, <hi>A dutiful Declaration of our affections, and loyalty, and purpoſe to ſupply his Majeſty in a Parliamentary-way, in a fitting and convenient time.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>This being done, the Speaker took the Chair, and admitting the Uſher, he declared his Meſſage from the Lords concerning the Diſſolution of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Now had the King an opportunity for his Summers paſt-time, but that his own progreſs might not impede that of his affairs, his Council were commanded to go along with him. By whoſe general advice, two things were moſt conſiderably reſolved upon:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Fleet ſhould ſpeedily be put to Sea.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> That a more ſtrict Amity ſhould be enter'd into with the States of the United Provinces.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Several were the Deſcants of ſuch as pretended to judicious cenſure, as fancy and affection ſwayed the ballance; ſome blamed the Parliament for not ſupplying the Kings neceſſities, whereby the Fleet put forth too late; ſome reflected finiſterly upon the Duke, ſaying, It never was, nor never will be well with <hi>England,</hi> while the Sea is under the Command of an Admiral ſo young, and withal ſo unexperienc'd; others alſo made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction from this miſcarriage of <hi>Gades</hi> Voyage, in reference to the King; that becauſe Commencements do often foreſpeak the qualification of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture contingencies in the ſeries and row of ſucceeding affairs; they much feared this was but the earneſt of ſome inauſpiciouſneſs which would attend the reſidue of his Reign: Nor, among the reſt, was Captain <hi>Brett</hi>'s conjecture vain, who told the Duke, That the Fleet was never like to ſpeed better, wherein there went a long Bag without Money, Cook without Meat, and Love without Charity; for ſo were the three Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains named; and a great default there was doubtleſs of ſufficient pay, of wholeſome meat, and unanimity.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Michaelmas</hi>-Term was by reaſon of the infection at <hi>London,</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to <hi>Reading;</hi> from whence the King, according to late Anſwer in Parliament, iſſued out in <hi>November</hi> a Commiſſion to the Judges, to ſee the Laws againſt Recuſants put in Execution.</p>
            <p>This Commiſſion was read in all the Courts of Judicature at <hi>Reading,</hi> and withal a Letter was directed to the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning him to take ſpecial care within his Province, for the diſcovery of <hi>Jeſuits, Seminary-Prieſts,</hi> and other Recuſants, offenders againſt the Laws. It was, in truth, high time for ſevere Proceedings againſt them, they having contracted ſo much inſolence, and preſuming upon protection, by reaſon of the late Match; that at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and many other places, they fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59492:12"/>paſſed through the Churches in time of Divine Service, hooting and hallowing, not only to the diſturbance of that duty, but to the ſcorn of our Religion; yea, and one Popiſh Lord, when the King was at Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, was heard to prate on purpoſe louder in a Gallery adjoyning, than the Chaplain prayed; whereat the King was ſo moved, that he ſent this Meſſage too him, <hi>viz.</hi> Either let him come and do as we do, or elſe I will make him prate farther off.</p>
            <p>On <hi>February</hi> the <hi>2d,</hi> this year, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1625, the King was Crowned at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> with the uſual (though I cannot ſay Magnificent) Ceremonies and Solemnities.</p>
            <p>The Coronation being paſt, the King prepareth for a Parliament now approaching; the laſt he thought was ſomewhat uncivil towards the Duke; and the Delinquents (as he thought) muſt be made examples: Upon this account the Lord-Keeper <hi>Williams,</hi> ſoon after the Diſſolution of the late Parliament, fell, and his place was diſpoſed of to Sir <hi>Thomas Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>On the <hi>16th</hi> of this <hi>February,</hi> the Parliament met; the Commons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan their work, where they laſt broke off at <hi>Oxford,</hi> making Religion their firſt, and which was their ſuperlative care; recollecting what a full and ſatisfactory Anſwer the King gave to their Petition againſt Recuſants, and his Commiſſion iſſued out in purſuance of that Anſwer, appointed a Committee for Religion, impowring them moſt ſtrictly to examine what abuſes of his Majeſties Grace had occurred ſince that time, and who were the Authors and Abettors of the ſame.</p>
            <p>The Houſe of Commons being in expectation of ſome Diſcovery from their Committee, at length Mr. <hi>Prin</hi> made a report of a Letter written to the Lord Mayor of <hi>York,</hi> for reprieving ſome Jeſuits, Prieſts, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Recuſants. This Letter being under the <hi>Signet,</hi> a ſub-Committee was ordered to ſearch the <hi>Signet-Office,</hi> and compare it with the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal.</p>
            <p>Theſe Proceedings inwardly much diſpleaſed the King, yet he ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered the indignity for a time, though he did after intimate the ſame unto them among his other regrets: And plying his more important af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs with a moſt ſteady temper, he ſent a Meſſage unto them by Sir <hi>Richard Weſton,</hi> to this effect, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That his Fleet is returned, and their Victuals ſpent; the Men muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be diſcharged, and their wages paid them, or elſe mutiny will follow, which may be of dangerous conſequence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That he hath in readineſs about</hi> 40 <hi>Ships, to be ſet forth upon a ſecond ſervice, which want a preſent ſupply of moneys.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Armies, quartered on the Coasts, want Victuals and Cloaths; and they will Disband, if not furniſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Companies of</hi> Ireland <hi>lately ſent, must ſpeedily be provided for, elſe they may be ſubject to rebel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly, The ſeaſon for providing healthful proviſion will be paſt, if this Month of</hi> March <hi>be ſuffered through negligence to elapſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore he deſired to know without more ado what preſent ſupplies he muſt depend upon from them, that ſo accordingly he might ſhape his courſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59492:13"/>
Inſtead of a ſupply to his Meſſage, Mr. <hi>Clement Coke</hi> (Son to Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Coke</hi>) a Member of the Houſe of Commons, let fly this reply: <hi>It is better to dye by a Foreign Enemy, than to be deſtroyed at home;</hi> and as if the Prerogative had not been ſufficiently alarm'd by that expreſſion, one <hi>Turner,</hi> a Doctor of Phyſick, re-aſſaults it in theſe ſix Queries:
<list>
                  <item>1. Whether the King hath not loſt the Regality of the Narrow Seas ſince the Duke became Admiral?</item>
                  <item>2. Whether his going in the laſt Fleet as Admiral, was not the cauſe of ill ſucceſs?</item>
                  <item>3. Whether the Kings Revenue hath not been impaired through his immenſe liberality?</item>
                  <item>4. Whether he hath not ingroſſed all Offices, and preferred his kindred to unfit places?</item>
                  <item>5. Whether he hath not made ſale of places of Judicature?</item>
                  <item>6. Whether Recuſants have not dependance upon his Mother and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-law?</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>This was uncouth language to a Princes Ear; but who can expect that in ſo vaſt a Body and Maſs of men, all parcels ſhould take ſalt alike, and that no part ſhould have rancidity in it? Yet perhaps this clamour and noiſe might be the rudeneſs of ſome few, newly admitted into that great School of Wiſdom, the greater part continuing (it's poſſible) ſincere and loyal; therefore the King ſends Sir <hi>Richard Weſton</hi> to them, requiring ſatisfaction: But the Houſe was flower in the work, than was agreeable to his Majeſties mind, ſo intent upon ſome ſevere Proceedings againſt them. Upon this he called the Lords and them together, and by the Lord-Keeper, his proper Speaker, thus conveys his diſpleaſure to them; which being ſomewhat long, and afterwards the Kings Speech alſo to them, I ſhall refer you to the Book it ſelf, <hi>Page</hi> 24, 25, 26.</p>
            <p>The Commons nothing moved with thoſe tart and vinacre expreſſions, kept cloſe to their proper ſtations, and by way of Remonſtrance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied: the which you may peruſe <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>27th</hi> of the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>To the Remonſtrance the King anſwered briefly, That he would have them, in the firſt place, conſult about matters of the greateſt importance, and that they ſhould have time enough for other things afterwards.</p>
            <p>But the Parliament accounted nothing of ſo great importance, as a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous proceeding againſt the Duke. In order to which, all encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is given by both Houſes to any who would inform againſt him. The Earl of <hi>Briſtol</hi> vigilantly liſtned for this call, and preſently Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Houſe, he might be admitted to prefer an Accuſation againſt him; His requeſt is readily granted. The Duke alarm'd with this Petition, Plots amain (and high time) either to divert or encounter him: He perſwades the King to ſend the Earl a Premonitary-Letter, framed as a Memorial, minding him of all the miſcarriages relating to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Treaty, and a Breviate of what became of his future charge; and demanding withal his poſitive Anſwer, Whether he would ſit ſtill from being queſtioned for any Errors paſt in his <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Negotiations, and enjoy the benefit of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don granted by the late Parliament; or waving the advantage thereof, put himſelf upon a Legal Tryal.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:59492:13"/>
To this the Earl anſwered, That it became him not as a Subject to urge a Tryal againſt himſelf; but if His Majeſty ſhould call him to it, he would willingly ſubmit, being confident his innocence would mediate for his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture favour: As for the Pardon, he would not diſclaim it, though he was confident he ſhould not need it for any Crime of Diſloyalty to His Majeſty, or Treaſon againſt the State.</p>
            <p>The King perceiving by this Reply the Earl reſolved to perſiſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Attorney-General to Summon the Earl to the Lords Bar as a Delinquent, <hi>May</hi> the <hi>1ſt. Briſtol</hi> appearing, the Attorney told the Peers, That he came thither to accuſe the Earl of High-Treaſon; with that the Earl ſaid, My Lords, I am a Freeman, and a Peer of the Realm, unat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted; I have ſomewhat to ſay of high conſequence for his Majeſties Service; I beſeech your Lordſhips give me leave to ſpeak: The Lords bidding him go on: Then, ſaid he, I accuſe that Man the Duke of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham</hi> of High-Treaſon: the Articles of his Charge you may read <hi>Page</hi> 28. <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Earl had ended his Charge, up ſtarts no upſtart Lord, the Lord <hi>Spencer,</hi> Is this all (ſaid he) you have to ſay againſt the Duke? The Earl replied, Yes my Lord, and I am ſorry it is ſo much: Then quoth the Lord <hi>Spencer,</hi> if this be all, <hi>Ridiculus Mus;</hi> and ſo ſat down again.</p>
            <p>Upon this a Crotchet took the Lord <hi>Cromwell</hi> in the Crown, and out he goes to Mr. <hi>Richard Spencer,</hi> a younger Son of that Lord, and a great Zealot in the lower Houſe againſt the Duke: <hi>Dick,</hi> ſaid he, what is done in your Houſe to day againſt the Duke? My Lord (ſaid he) he is charged with no leſs than High-Treaſon: Tuſh <hi>Dick,</hi> quoth the Lord, High-Treaſon! if this be all, <hi>Ridiculus Mus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This high and daring challenging by the Earl, prompted the Attorney to ſpeed his Accuſation againſt him; which having Modell'd into Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Articles, he brought in the next day, <hi>Vide page</hi> 28. <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Commons having preſented their Accuſation, preſently after ſent a Meſſage to the Lords, deſiring that the Duke might be Committed; declaring, that it did miſ-beſeem their Houſe to permit a man ſo deeply Impeacht to ſit in Councel with them.</p>
            <p>The Court-party, who had nimble Intelligencers, underſtood this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign from the very firſt reſult, and plotted to treat the Commons with uniform Proceedings; for at that very time Sir <hi>Dudley Diggs,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Elliot</hi> were ſent for out of the Houſe by two Meſſengers of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; who upon their coming forth, ſhewed them Warrants for their Commitment to the <hi>Tower;</hi> but it was reſolved by the Judges, that by their reſtraint (no reaſon being given to the Houſe for it) the whole Houſe was arreſted, and a Remonſtrance was made to the King of their Priviledg; whereupon they were releaſed.</p>
            <p>The Commons having ſped ſo well, the Houſe of Peers began to claim their immunities; making an Order, that nothing ſhould be tranſacted in their Houſe, until the Earl of <hi>Arundel</hi> were reſtored; upon which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly enſued the Earls Poſtlimination and re-admittance.</p>
            <p>Popular diſguſt began now to break in upon the Duke, with ſuch a running and ſweeping-tide, as drew along with it, by way of Concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy, the Peerage; nor could his new Dependents and Allies keep the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance Horizontial, and even much leſs ſway it; and becauſe his fate muſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59492:14"/>reſult from them, but not by weight, but tale; the old Trick of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> was thought upon, and a new Summons of Perſons former Confidents to the Duke (as the Lords, <hi>Mandevil, Grandiſon</hi> and <hi>Carlton</hi>) into the row of Nobles.</p>
            <p>But this project would not take; for the Houſe of Lords found an ancient Order, That no Lords created <hi>ſedente Parliamento,</hi> ſhall have Voices during that Seſſion, but only ſhall have priviledg of ſitting among the reſt; upon which their ſuffrage was excluded.</p>
            <p>This gave the Duke a taſte (a bitter one) of their inclinations; ſo that finding but ſmall favour to truſt to, he magnanimouſly ſtood upon his Juſtification. And having his defence to his contentment, <hi>June</hi> the <hi>8th,</hi> 1626, he preſented it to the Lords; who upon receipt thereof, ſequeſtred him from ſitting any more as a Peer of the Houſe, until his Cauſe was determined; whereupon he went away much dejected.</p>
            <p>The Dukes Defence, and the Commons Impeachment being long, I ſhall not here inſert, but refer you to the <hi>Annals</hi> it ſelf, from whom I do tranſcribe this ſmall Narrative.</p>
            <p>This weighty Cauſe was managed by ſix Gentlemen, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Glanvil,</hi> Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pim,</hi> Mr. <hi>VVansford,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sherland,</hi> to whom was added Sir <hi>Dudley Diggs</hi> as Foreman and Prolocutor, and Sir <hi>John Elliot</hi> to bring up the rear.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Dudley Diggs</hi> his Prologue, for the extraordinary Elegancy of the frame, and conciſeneſs of his Metaphors, I ſhall crave leave to inſert as it was delivered unto the Lords before the Gentlemen of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons did preſent the 13 Grievances, expreſly this.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My LORDS,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THere are ſo many things of great importance to be ſaid in a very little time this day, that I conceive it will not be unacceptable unto your Lordſhips, if (ſetting aſide all Rhetorical affectations) I only in plain Countrey language, humbly pray your Lordſhips favour to include many excuſes, neceſſary to my many infirmities.</p>
                  <p>In this one word, I am commanded by the Knights, Citizens and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes of the Commons Houſe to preſent unto your Lordſhips their moſt affectionate Thanks for your ready condeſcending to this Conference; which out of confidence in your great Wiſdoms, and approved Juſtice for the ſervice of his Majeſty, and the welfare of this Realm, they deſired upon this occaſion.</p>
                  <p>The Houſe of Commons, by a fatal and univerſal concurrence of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints from all the Seabordering parts of this Kingdom, did find a great and grievous interruption and ſtop of Trade and Traffick: The baſe Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates of <hi>Sally</hi> ignominiouſly infeſting our Coaſts; taking our Ships and Goods, and leading away the Subjects of this Kingdom into Barbarous Captivity, while to our ſhame, and hinderance of Commerce, our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies did (as it were) Beſiege our Ports, and Block up our beſt Rivers Mouths, our Friends on ſlight pretences made Embargoes of our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Goods, and every Nation (upon the leaſt occaſion) was ready to contemn and ſlight us: So great was the apparent diminution of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Honour of this Crown, and once ſtrong reputation of our Nation;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59492:14"/>wherewith the Commons were more troubled, calling to remembrance, how formerly in <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> and everywhere by Sea and Land, the Valours of this Kingdom had been better valued; and even in latter times, within remembrance, when we had no Alliance with <hi>France,</hi> none in <hi>Denmark,</hi> none in <hi>Germany,</hi> no Friend in <hi>Italy,</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to ſay no more, united <hi>Ireland,</hi> not ſetled in peace, and much leſs ſecurity at home; when <hi>Spain</hi> was as ambitious as it is now under a King (<hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> the Second) they called their Wiſeſt; the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> as great and Potent, and both ſtrengthned with a Malicious League in <hi>France</hi> of perſons ill-affected, when the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> had no being; yet by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Councels, and Old <hi>Engliſh</hi> ways, even then that <hi>Spaniſh</hi> pride was cool'd, that greatneſs of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> ſo formidable to us now, was well reſiſted, and to the United Provinces of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> ſuch a beginning, growth and ſtrength was given, as gave us Honour over all the Chriſtian World.</p>
                  <p>The Commons therefore wondring at the evils which they ſuffered, debating of the cauſes of them, found they were many, drawn like one Line to one Circumference of Decay of Trade and Strength, of Honour and Reputation, in this Kingdom, which as in one Centre, met in one great man, the cauſe of all, whom I am here to name, the Duke of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Here Sir</hi> Dudley Diggs <hi>made a ſtand, as wondring to ſee the Duke pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; yet he took the Roll, and read the Preamble to the Charge, with the Duke's Titles, which I ſhall here, for the Readers Satisfaction, inſert, and ſo proceed.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="preamble">
               <body>
                  <p>For the ſpeedy Redreſs of the great evils and miſchiefs,<note place="margin">The Preamble to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Duke of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham.</hi>
                     </note> and of the chief cauſes of thoſe evils and miſchiefs, which this Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> now grievouſly ſuffereth, and of late years hath ſuffered, and to the honour and ſafety of our Soveraign Lord the King, and of his Crown and Digni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, and to the good and welfare of his People; The Commons in this preſent Parliament, by the Authority of our Soveraign Lord the King aſſembled, do by this their Bill, ſhew and declare againſt <hi>George,</hi> Duke, Marqueſs, and Earl of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> Earl of <hi>Coventry,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Villers,</hi> Baron of <hi>Whaddon,</hi> Great Admiral of the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and of the Principality of <hi>Wales,</hi> and of the Dominions and Iſlands of the ſame; of the Town of <hi>Calais,</hi> and of the Marches of the ſame, and of <hi>Normandy, Gaſcoin,</hi> and <hi>Guyen:</hi> General Governor of the Seas and Ships of the ſaid Kingdoms, Lieutenant-General, Admiral, Captain-General, and Governor of his Majeſties Royal Fleet and <hi>Armado,</hi> lately ſet forth. Maſter of the Horſe of our Soveraign Lord the King, Lord Warden, Chancellor, and Admiral of the Cinque-Ports, and of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, Conſtable of <hi>Dover-Caſtle,</hi> Juſtice in <hi>Eyre</hi> of all Foreſts and Chaſes on this ſide of the River of <hi>Trent,</hi> Conſtable of the Caſtle of <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> Lieutenant of <hi>Middleſex</hi> and <hi>Buckinghamſhire,</hi> Steward and Bayliff of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Gentleman of his Majeſties Bed-Chamber, and one of his Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Council, in his Realms both of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Knight of the moſt Noble Order of the Garter.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:59492:15"/>
               <hi>The Miſdemeanors, Miſpriſions, Offences, Crimes, and other matters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized in the Articles following: And him the ſaid Duke do Accuſe and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach of the ſaid Miſdemeanors, Miſpriſions, Offences and Crimes.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>And now my Lords,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>This lofty Title of this mighty man, methinks doth raiſe my Spirits to ſpeak with a <hi>Paulo majora canamus;</hi> and let it not diſpleaſe your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, if for Foundation I compare the beautiful Structure and fair Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of this Monarchy, wherein we live, to the great work of God, <hi>viz.</hi> the World it ſelf, in which the ſolid Body of incorporated Earth and Sea, as I conceive in regard of our Husbandry, Manufactures, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce by Land and Sea, may well reſemble us the Commons; and as it is encompaſſed with Air and Fire, and Spheres Celeſtial of Planets, and a Firmament of fixed Stars, all which receive their heat, light, and life, from one great glorious Sun, even like the King our Soveraign, ſo that Firmament of fixed Stars I take to be your Lordſhips; thoſe Planets, the great Officers of the Kingdom; that pure Element of Fire, the moſt Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Zealous, and Pious Clergy; and the Reverend Judges, Magiſtrates, and Miniſters of Law and Juſtice, the Air wherein we breathe, all which encompaſt round with cheriſhing, comfort this Body of the Commons, who truly labour for them all; and though they be the Footſtool and the loweſt, yet may well be ſaid to be the ſetled Centre of the State.</p>
                  <p>Now (my Lords) if that glorious Sun by his powerful Beams of Grace and Favour, ſhall draw from the bowels of this Earth an Exhalation, that ſhall fire, and burn, and ſhine out like a Star, it needs not be marvell'd at, if the poor Commons gaze and wonder at the Comet, when they feel the effects, and impute all to the corruptible matter thereof: But if ſuch an imperfect Meteor appear, like that in the laſt Age, in the Chair of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiopea,</hi> among the fixed Stars themſelves, where <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and the old Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers conceived there was no place for ſuch corruption;<note place="margin">The Meteor in 1680. is worth your obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon this very account.</note> then as the learned Mathematicians were troubled to obſerve the irregular motions, the prodigious magnitude, and the ominous Prognoſticks of that Meteor, ſo the Commons when they ſee ſuch a Blazing-Star in courſe ſo exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in the affairs of this Common-wealth, cannot but look up upon it, and for want of Perſpectives commend the nearer examination to your Lordſhips, who may behold it at a better diſtance. Such a prodigious Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met the Commons take this Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> to be,<note place="margin">And ſo the Commons do the Duke of <hi>York</hi> now, <hi>&amp; cum multis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis, &amp;c. Anno Domini,</hi> 1680 and 1681. and will doubtleſs ſeveral more, when they ſhall meet &amp; ſit to redreſs the preſent Grievances of the Nation.</note> againſt whom and his irregular ways, there are by learned Gentlemen legal Articles of Charge to be delivered to your Lordſhips, which I am generally firſt commanded to lay open,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, The Offices of this Kingdom, that are the Eyes, the Ears, and the Hands of this Common-wealth, theſe have been engroſſed, bought, and ſold, and many of the greateſt of them holden even in the Dukes own hands, which ſeverally and apart, gave in former times and ages ſufficient content to the greateſt Favourites, and were work enough for the wiſeſt Councellors: By means whereof what ſtrange abuſes, what infinite neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects have followed? The Seas have been unguarded, Trade diſturbed,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59492:15"/>Merchants oppreſſed, their Ships, and even one of the Navy Royal by cunning practiſe, delivered over into foreign hands, and contrary to our good Kings intention, employed to the prejudice (I had almoſt ſaid to the ruin) of Friends of our own Religion.</p>
                  <p>Next Honours (thoſe moſt precious Jewels of the Crown) a Treaſure ineſtimable, wherewith your Noble Anceſtors (my Lords) were well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded for eminent and publick ſervice in the Common-wealth at home, for brave exploits abroad, when covered all with duſt and blood, they ſweat in ſervice for the honour of this Crown: What back-ways, what by-ways have been by this Duke found out, is too well known to your Lordſhips; whereas it was anciently the honour of <hi>England</hi> (as among the <hi>Romans</hi>) the way to the Temple of Honour was through the Temple of Virtue: But I am commanded to preſs this no further, than to let your Lordſhips know, one Inſtance may (perhaps) be given of ſome one Lord, compelled to purchaſe Honour.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, as divers of the Dukes poor Kindred have been raiſed to great honours, which have been and are likely to be more chargeable and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſom to the Crown; ſo the Lands, and Revenues, and Treaſuries of his Majeſty have been intercepted, and exhauſted by this Duke and his Friends, and ſtrangely miſemployed with ſtrange confuſion of the Accompts, and overthrow of the well-eſtabliſhed ancient Orders of his Majeſties Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer.</p>
                  <p>The laſt of the Charges which are prepared, will be an injury offered to the Perſon of the late King of bleſſed memory, who is with God, of which (as your Lordſhips may have heard heretofore) you ſhall anon have farther information. Now upon this occaſion, I am commanded by the Commons, to take care of the honour of the King our Soveraign that lives (long may he live to our comfort and the good of the Chriſtian world) and alſo of his bleſſed Father who is dead, on whom to the grief of the Commons and their great diſtaſte, the Lord Duke did, they conceive, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily caſt ſome ill ordure of his own foul ways. Whereas Servants were anciently wont to bear (as in truth they ought) theit Maſters faults, and not caſt their own on them undeſervedly.</p>
                  <p>It is well known the King (who is with God) had the ſame power and the ſame wiſdom before he knew this Duke; yea and the ſame affections too, through which (as a good and gracious Maſter) he advanced and raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome Stars of your Lordſhips Firmament, in whoſe hands this exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy of Will, this tranſcendency of Power, ſuch placing and miſplacing of Officers, ſuch irregular running into all by courſes of the Planets, ſuch ſole and ſingle managing of the great affairs of State, was never heard of.</p>
                  <p>And therefore only to the Lord Duke, and his own procurement, by miſ-informations, theſe faults complained of by the Commons, are to be imputed.</p>
                  <p>And whereas for our moſt gracious Soveraign that lives, whoſe Name hath been uſed, and may perhaps now be for the Dukes Juſtification: The Commons know well, that among his Majeſties moſt Royal Virtues, his Piety unto his Father, hath made him a pious nouriſher of his Affections ever to this Lord Duke, on whom out of that conſideration his Majeſty hath wrought a kind of wonder, making Favour hereditary. But the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe thereof muſt be the Lord Dukes own; and if there have been any
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59492:16"/>commands, ſuch as were or may pretend, his miſinformations have procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them; whereas the Laws of <hi>England</hi> teach us, that Kings cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ill or unawful things whenever they ſpeak, though by their Letters Patents or their Seals: If the thing be evil, theſe Letters Patents are void; and whatſoever ill event ſucceeds, the Executioners of ſuch Commands muſt ever anſwer for them.</p>
                  <p>Thus, my Lords, in performance of my duty, my weakneſs hath been troubleſome unto your Lordſhips. It is now high time humbly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat your pardon, and to give way to a Learned Gentleman to begin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him a more particular Charge.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Sir <hi>Dudley Diggs</hi> his Prologue being ended, the Impeachment of the Commons it ſelf was next read; the which, if you pleaſe, you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe <hi>Page</hi> 40. in the ſaid Narrative before mentioned; with the Dukes Anſwer, Defence and Reply to every particular Article thereof.</p>
            <p>The Anſwer of the Duke to his Impeachment, was a kind of a new Grievance to his Adverſaries; for it being contrived, and ſo inlaid with modeſty and humility, it was like to have a powerful influence towards the converſion of many, who expected a Defence of another and more diſdainful ſpirit. Again, it ſeemed to inſtate him in impunity; and the Commons having charged him as they thought, through and through, loth they were to fall ſhort of Victory: And now having purſued him with ſuch vehemency, thought themſelves worſted, ſhould he now at the laſt make a ſaving game of it; wherefore reſolved they were to ply him with a ſpeedy Reply: But while they were hammering of it, the King ſent them a Letter, demanding, without farther delay, their ſpeedy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing their Bill of Subſidy to be paſſed; to which, to prevent their Diſſolution, they immediately conformed. But firſt they had drawn up a Declaration of the ſame make and mind with their former Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of the miſerable eſtate of this Kingdom, and not without ſome high Conteſts it was allowed by the Houſe before the Bill of Subſidy: Whereupon his Majeſty was ſo exceedingly incenſed,<note place="margin">King <hi>Charles</hi> his Second Parliament Diſſolved.</note> as on the very next day, <hi>June</hi> the <hi>5th,</hi> he Diſſolved the Aſſembly, though the Lords ſent four of their Houſe unto him, beſeeching him moſt earneſtly, that he would permit them to ſit but two days longer; but he anſwered, Not a Minute.</p>
            <p>The ſame afternoon the Earl of <hi>Briſtol,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arundel</hi> and <hi>Briſtol</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined.</note> the Dukes grand Proſecutor, was committed to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Arundel</hi> confined to his own houſe. There came alſo forth from his Majeſty a Proclamation, for Burning all the Copies of the Commons Declaration, made before the Parliaments Diſſolution.</p>
            <p>This Rupture of the Parliament,<note place="margin">The King charged with Imprudence.</note> being ſuppoſed to iſſue from the Kings great affection to the Duke, I find him charged with deep impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and high overſight, to hazard the Love of Millions for him only.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Monday,</hi> before this doleful diſaſter, there happened a terrible and prodigious ſpectacle upon the <hi>Thames:</hi> The Water near <hi>Lambeth-Marſh</hi> began about Three of the Clock in the afternoon to be very tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59492:16"/>and after a while, ariſing like a Miſt, it appeared in a Circular form about Ten yards Diameter, and about Ten foot elevated from the River. This Cataract, or Spout of Waters, was carried impetuouſly croſs the River, and made a very furious Aſſault upon the Garden-Walls of <hi>York</hi>-houſe (where the Duke was then building his new Water-Stairs); at length, after a fierce attempt, it brake aſunder, ſending up a fuliginous and dusky ſmoak, like that iſſuing out of a Brewers Chimney, which aſcended as high as was well diſcernable, and ſo vaniſht; and at the very ſame inſtant there was in the City of <hi>London</hi> ſo dreadful a ſtorm of Rain and Hail, with Thunder and Lightning, as a great part of the Church-Yard Wall of St. <hi>Andrews</hi> Church in <hi>Holbourn</hi> fell down; and divers Craves being thereby diſcovered, many Coffins tumbled into the middle of the Channel.</p>
            <p>Not long after this there fell out a difference between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France;</hi> and his Majeſty, in proceſs of time, being on every ſide on the loſing hand, he was much diſtreſſed in mind, what courſe to take to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge himſelf of thoſe impendent Calamities; ſhould he call a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">The King in great want.</note> the time (whoſe every moment was precious unto him) would not permit to ſtay for their Convention; and when met, ſhould they prove (as it was odds they would) as Dilatory and diſguſtful as the former, he were in a worſe condition than before. In this perplexed difficulty, at length his Council agreed to ſet that great Engine, his Prerogative, at work: Many projects were hammered on that forge, but they came all to ſmall effect.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they moved for a Contribution, by way of Benevolence; but this was ſoon daſht. Then a reſolution was taken to advance the value of Coyn Two ſhillings in the pound; but this alſo was ſoon argued down by Sir <hi>Robert Cotton:</hi> But that which the Council ſtuck cloſeſt to, was the iſſuing of a Commiſſion,<note place="margin">Raiſeth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by Loan.</note> dated <hi>October</hi> the <hi>13th,</hi> for raiſing almoſt Two hundred thouſand younds by way of <hi>Loan;</hi> and the more to expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite and facilitate this Levy, the Commiſſioners were inſtructed to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Subject the deplorable eſtate of <hi>Rochel,</hi> then cloſely beleaguer'd by the Duke of <hi>Guiſe;</hi> and if not ſpeedily relieved, would fall irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably into the hands of the Enemies of the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>Theſe were plauſible inſinuations: For <hi>Rochel,</hi> though ſcituated in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countrey, yet was looked upon as in the ſame parallel Belief with us. And what will not men ſuffer for others of the ſame perſwaſion, eſpecially when Fame reports them ſufferers becauſe of the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion?</p>
            <p>But all would not ſmooth the aſperity of this moſt Illegal Tax. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel,</hi> and all other Foreign Conſiderations muſt ſtand by, and aloof off, when homebred Liberty is diſputed; ſo thought the almoſt Majority of the Kingdom, who oppoſed it to <hi>Durance.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Many refuſe.</note> Upon this account of refuſal, Priſoners, ſome of the Nobility, and moſt of the prime Gentry, were daily brought in by ſcores, I might almoſt ſay by Counties; ſo that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil-Table had almoſt as much work to provide Priſons, as to ſupply the Kings neceſſities.</p>
            <p>This year Learning loſt two Luminaries of the greateſt Magnitude that ever this Nation enjoyed, <hi>viz.</hi> Dr. <hi>Andrews,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>VVincheſter,</hi> and Sir <hi>Francis Bacon,</hi> Vicount St. <hi>Albans,</hi> Lord High Chancellor of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:59492:17"/>
The Commiſſion of Loan not anſwering in its product his Majeſties ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, the Papiſts began now to plot their own advantage from the Kings wants; and under pretence of Loyalty, they of <hi>Ireland</hi> propounded to him, That upon conſideration of a Toleration of their Religion, they would at their own charge furniſh him with a conſtant Army of five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Foot and five hundred Horſe. But this project to their great regret proved Dow-baked, the Proteſtants countermining them: For in the next Spring Doctor <hi>Downham,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> Preaching before the Lord Deputy and the whole State, <hi>April</hi> 22. 1627. taking for his Text, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74. <hi>That we being delivered from the hands of our Enemies, might ſerve him without fear.</hi> In the midſt of his Sermon, he openly read this Proteſtation, ſubſcribed by the Archbiſhops and all the Biſhops of that Kingdom.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That the Religion of the Papiſts is Superſtitious and Idolatrous.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Their Faith and Doctrine Erroneous and Heretical.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Their Church in reſpect of both, Apoſtatical.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>To give them therefore a Toleration, is to make our ſelves acceſſary to their abominations, and to the perdition of their Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But to ſell them a Toleration, is to ſet Religion to ſale, and with that their Souls, which Chriſt hath redeemed with his moſt precious blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Biſhop having ended this Proteſtation, added: <hi>And let all the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſay Amen,</hi> which they did ſo as the Church almoſt ſhook with the noiſe. The Deputy required of the Biſhop a Copy of both his Sermon and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, who anſwered he would moſt willingly juſtifie it before his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and feared not to read it.</p>
            <p>And now although moneys came in but ſlowly, yet was the Naval Force completed for expedition about Midſummer; whereof the Duke appeared Admiral; as ambitious of ſome meritorious ſervice to earn a better guſt, or to correct the univerſal <hi>odium</hi> againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 27th he ſet Sail from <hi>Portſmouth</hi> with about ſix thouſand Horſe and Foot; and <hi>July</hi> the eleventh he publiſhed a <hi>Manifeſto,</hi> declaring the impulſive cauſes of his Majeſties preſent Arming.</p>
            <p>But the Duke had very ill ſucceſs in this expedition; for the Engliſh were routed at the Iſle of <hi>Rhe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Engliſh routed at the Iſle of <hi>Rhe.</hi>
               </note> the ſum of their loſs were about fifty Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers (but the greateſt loſs was that gallant man, Sir <hi>John Burroughs,</hi> who was ſlain by a Muſquet Bullet from the Citadel, while he was viewing the Engliſh works;) of Common Soldiers few leſs than two thouſand, Priſoners of Note thirty five, Colours taken forty four, hung up as Anthems at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> in the Church of <hi>Noſtredame,</hi> our Honour loſt. The Priſoners <hi>Lewis</hi> graciouſly diſmiſt home, as an affectionate offertory to his Siſter the Queen of <hi>England;</hi> which made up another Victory ſuperadded to the former, and a conqueſt over us as well in the exerciſe of civilities, as in feat of Arms; only the Lord <hi>Montjoy</hi> was ranſomed, for the which he offering to the French King a round ſum; <hi>No my Lord,</hi> it is ſaid the King replied, <hi>your Redemption ſhall be only two couple of Hounds from</hi> England: Some inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted this a ſlender value of that Lord, to be exchanged for a couple of Dogs; but it was only in the King a modeſt eſtimate of his courteſie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:59492:17"/>
The <hi>Rochellers</hi> being beſieged by the <hi>French</hi> King,<note place="margin">The <hi>Rochelers</hi> crave our Kings aid.</note> in their diſtreſs hurrieth and ſerrieth over their Deputies to <hi>England</hi> to ſolicit our King for freſh ſupplies, before the prodigious work ſhould be compleated; who (good Prince) affected with their Miſeries, and deſirous rather to protect them from being ſlaves, than to enable them to be Maſters, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended to aſſure them of what aſſiſtance he could make.</p>
            <p>But, alas! what could his aſſiſtance ſignifie, who was as neceſſitous as themſelves? Did they want Men, Ammunition-Ships? So did he, ſeeing he wanted that which was all theſe, Money; and how, and where ſhould that be had? His laſt borrowing Commiſſions, was a courſe ſo diſpleaſing to the Subject, as would not admit of repetition, and it would prove an odd payment of that Loan arrears, to demand another: But the King was now the Subject of a greater Potentate than himſelf, Neceſſity; and this Neceſſity put him upon ſeveral projects: Firſt he borroweth of the Common-Council of <hi>London,</hi> One hundred and twenty thouſand pounds; for which, and other debts, he aſſures unto them Twenty-one thouſand pounds <hi>per annum</hi> of his own Lands: and of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company Thirty thouſand pounds; and yet he wants. Next, Privy-Seals are ſent out by Hundreds, and a new way of Levy by Exciſe, reſolved to be executed by Commiſſion, Dated the <hi>3d</hi> of <hi>February;</hi> and yet he wants: but the beſt and moſt taking project of all, was a Parliament; whereby he hoped not only to ſupply his neceſſities, but alſo to give ſome better repoſe to his troubled ſpirit; for he felt no inward contentment, whilſt he the Head and the Body were at a diſtance, or like interſects and flies, tackt together by a Mathematical line, or imaginary thread; therefore he ſeriouſly reſolved for his part to frame and diſpoſe himſelf to ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging complacency and compliance, as might re-conſolidate, and make them knit again.</p>
            <p>This Parliament was Summoned to meet on the <hi>17th</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1627;<note place="margin">King <hi>Charles</hi> his Third Parliament aſſembled, <hi>March</hi> 17, 1627.</note> and the Writs being iſſued out, the <hi>Loan</hi>-Recuſants appeared the only men in the Peoples affections; none thought worthy of a Patriots title, but he that was under reſtraint upon that account; ſo that the far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number of the Parliament was formed of them: And as their Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings had made them of Eminent remark for Noble Courage, ſo did they for External reſpects appear the gallanteſt Aſſembly that ever thoſe Walls immured; they having Eſtates modeſtly eſtimated, able to buy the Houſe of Peers (the King excepted), One hundred and eighteen, thrice over. Thus were all things ſtrangely turned in a trice topſide t'other way: they who lately were confin'd as Priſoners, are now not only free, but petty Lords and Maſters, yea, and petty Kings.</p>
            <p>Some few days before this Seſſion, a notable diſcovery was made of a Colledge of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> at <hi>Clerkenwell.</hi> The firſt Information was given by one <hi>Croſs,</hi> a Meſſenger to Secretary <hi>Coke,</hi> who ſent a Warrant to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <hi>Long,</hi> dwelling near enjoyning, to take ſome Conſtables, and other aid with him, and forthwith to beſet the houſe, and apprehend the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> entring at firſt door, they found at ſtairs-foot a Man and a Woman ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who told them, My Maſters, take heed you go not up the ſtairs, for there are above many reſolute and valiant Men, who are well provided with Swords and Piſtols, and will loſe their lives rather than yield; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you love your lives, be gone. The Conſtable took their counſel,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59492:18"/>and like cowardly Buzzards went their way, and told Secretary <hi>Coke</hi> the danger; whereupon the Secretary ſent the Sheriff to attack them, who coming with a formidable Power, found all withdrawn and ſneakt away; but after a long ſearch, their place of ſecurity was found out, it being a Lobby behind a new Brick-wall, Wainſcoated over; which being demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht, they were preſently unkennel'd, to the number of Ten. They found alſo divers Letters from the Pope to them, empowring them to erect this Colledge under the name of <hi>Domus Probationis</hi> (but it proved <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probationis</hi>) <hi>Sancti Ignatii;</hi> and their Books of Accounts, whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared they had Five hundred pounds <hi>per annum</hi> contribution from their Benefactors, and had likewiſe purchaſed Four hundred and fifty pounds <hi>per annum;</hi> they had a Chappel, Library, and other Rooms of neceſſary accommodation, with Houſhold-utenſils and implements marked † <hi>S.</hi> What became of theſe <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> will fall in afterward: and what would have become of the Secretary for his double diligence in their proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you ſhould have heard, had not the Duke been cut off by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely end to himſelf, but timely to the Popular Guſt.</p>
            <p>The Parliament being met, the King began thus to them:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THeſe times are for Action:<note place="margin">The Kings Speech.</note> for Action I ſay, not for Words; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall uſe but few; and (as Kings are ſaid to be Exemplary to their Subjects) I wiſh you would imitate me in this, and uſe as few, falling upon ſpeedy conſultation. No man is, I conceive, ſuch a ſtranger to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Neceſſity, as to expoſtulate the cauſe of this Meeting, and not to think Supply to be the end of it: And as this Neceſſity is the product and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of your advice; ſo the true Religion, the Laws and Liberties of this State, and juſt defence of our Friends and Allies, being ſo conſiderably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, will be, I hope, arguments enough to perſwade ſupply: For if it be, as moſt true it is, both my Duty and yours to preſerve this Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, this exigent time certainly requires it. In this time of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon danger I have taken the moſt ancient, ſpeedy, and beſt way for ſupply, by calling you together; if (which God forbid) in not contributing what may anſwer the Quality of my occaſions, you do not your Duties, it ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice I have done mine, in the conſcience whereof I ſhall reſt content, and take ſome other courſe, for which God hath impower'd me to ſave that which the folly of particular men might hazard to loſe.</p>
                  <p>Take not this as a Menace (for I ſcorn to threaten my Inferiors), but as an Admonition from him who is tyed both by Nature and Duty, to provide for your preſervations: And I hope, though I thus ſpeak, your Demeanors will be ſuch as ſhall oblige me in thankfulneſs to meet you oftener, than which nothing ſhall be more pleaſing unto me.</p>
                  <p>Remembring the diſtractions of our laſt Meeting, you may ſuppoſe I have no confidence of good ſucceſs at this time: but be aſſured, I ſhall freely forget and forgive what is paſt, hoping you will follow that ſacred advice lately incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, To maintain the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59492:18"/>
The Parliament ſeemed at firſt exceeding prompt to cloſe with the Kings deſires, and as complyingly diſpoſed as could be wiſhed; but they had not forgot the many preſſures, which made the ſubject groan; ſomething they muſt do for them who ſent, as well as for him who called them thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and to anticipate all manner of diſpute in point of Precedence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Subjects grievances, and the Kings ſupplies, they make an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that both ſhould proceed <hi>pari paſſu,</hi> cheek by joul.</p>
            <p>Upon full conſideration of the Kings wants,<note place="margin">The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment grant liberally.</note> they preſently and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully agreed to give him five Subſidies, whereof Secretary <hi>Coke</hi> was the firſt Evangeliſt, and Porter of that good news to the King, who received it with wondrous joy, and asked the Secretary by how many Voices it was carried? Sir <hi>John</hi> replyed, but by one: At which perceiving the Kings countenance to change; Sir, ſaid he, your Majeſty hath the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cauſe to rejoyce; for the Houſe was ſo unanimous therein, as that they made but one voice; whereupon the King wept, and bad the Secretary tell them, He would deny them nothing of their Liberties, which any of his Predeceſſors had granted.</p>
            <p>The ſtream of affairs running thus ſmoothly,<note place="margin">The Subjects Libetty under debate.</note> without the leaſt wrinkle of diſcontent on either ſide; the Houſe of Commons firſt inſiſted upon the Perſonal Freedom of the People, and reſolved for Law, That no Freeman ought to be impriſoned, either by the King or Council, without a legal Cauſe alledged. This opinion of the Houſe was reported to the Lords, at a Conference by Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> Sir <hi>Dudley Diggs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Littleton;</hi> Sir <hi>Dudley Diggs</hi> citing <hi>Acts</hi> 25. <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. It ſeemeth an unreaſonable thing to ſend a Priſoner, and not withal to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the Crimes laid againſt him.</p>
            <p>This buſineſs ſtuck very much in the Lords Houſe,<note place="margin">The Lords nice in the buſineſs.</note> who were willing that the Nails ſhould be pared, not the hands tyed of the Prerogative; ſeveral and great Debates there were about it. The Attorney pleading eagerly (though impertinently) for the King; and the ancient Records were ſo direct for the People, and ſo ſtrongly enforced, as the Attorney had no more to ſay, but only, I refer my ſelf to the Judgment of the Lords; and when theſe Lords were to give Judgment concerning it, the Ducal, or Royal party (for they were both one) were ſo prevalent, as they who leaned the other way, durſt not abide the Tryal by Vote; but calling the Lord-Keeper down, moulded the Houſe into a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, until the Lord <hi>Say</hi> made a motion, That they who ſtood for the Liberties (being effective about fifty) might make their Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and that to be upon Record: And that the other oppoſite party ſhould alſo with Subſcriptions of their Names, enter their Reaſons, to remain alſo upon Record, that ſo Poſterity might not be to ſeek who they were, who ſo ignobly betrayed the Freedom of our Nation; and that this done, they ſhould proceed to a Vote: At which the Court-party were ſo daunted, as that they durſt not mutter one ſyllable againſt it.</p>
            <p>Perſonal Liberty being thus ſetled; next they fall upon Liberty of Goods, the unbilleting of Soldiers, and nulling of Martial-Law in times of Peace; and finding <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and ſix other Statutes explanatory of it, to be expreſly on their ſide, they Petitioned the King to grant
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59492:19"/>them the benefit of them; whereupon he declared Himſelf, by the Lord-Keeper, unto them <hi>in his Verbis:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>That He did hold the Statutes of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the ſix other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted upon for the Subjects Liberty, to be all in force; and aſſured them, that he would maintain all his Subjects in the juſt freedom of their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſafety of Eſtates; and that he would govern according to the Laws and Statutes of the Realm; and that his People ſhould find as much ſecurity in his Royal Word and Promiſe, as in any Laws they could make; ſo that hereafter they ſhould have no cauſe to complain; and therefore he deſired no doubt nor diſtruſt might poſſeſs any man, but that they would proceed ſpeedily and unanimouſly on with their buſineſs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Meſſage begat a new Queſtion, Whether or no his Majeſty ſhould be truſted upon his Royal Word? Some thought it needleſs, becauſe of his Coronation-Oath, binding him to maintain the Laws of the Land: That Oath was as ſtrong as any Royal Word could be. Others were of opinion, That ſhould it be put to Vote, and carried in the Negative, it would be infinitely diſhonourable unto him in Foreign parts, who would be ready to ſay, The People of <hi>England</hi> would not truſt their King upon his Royal Promiſe.</p>
            <p>At length, in the height of this Diſpute, ſtands up Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> and thus informed the Houſe: We ſit now in Parliament, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt take his Majeſties Word no otherwiſe than in a Parliamentary-way; that is, The King ſitting on his Throne in his Royal Robes, his Crown on his Head, his Scepter in his Hand in full Parliament, both Houſes being preſent, all theſe Circumſtances obſerved, and his Aſſent being entred upon a Record, make his Royal Word the Word of a King in Parliament, and not a word delivered in a Chamber, or at ſecond hand by the mouth of a Secretary or Lord-Keeper; therefore his Motion was, That the Houſe ſhould <hi>(More Majorum)</hi> according to the cuſtom of their Predeceſſors, draw a Petition <hi>(De Droict)</hi> of Right to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; which being confirmed by both Houſes, and aſſented unto by the King, would be as firm an Act as any.</p>
            <p>This Judgment of ſo great a Father in the Law,<note place="margin">The Petition of Right pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by this Parliament.</note> at this time ruled all the Houſe, and accordingly a Petition was framed, and at a Conference preſented unto the Lords, the ſubſtance whereof (after the recital of ſeveral Statutes relating to the Priviledge of the Subject) was reduced to four Heads.</p>
            <p>The Petition being preſented to his Majeſty after two ſeveral An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers thereunto (which did not pleaſe the Parliament), he did the third time give them this Anſwer (the Petition being read) thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Le droict ſoit faict comme il eſt deſire.</hi> This I am ſure is full, yet no more than I granted you in my firſt Anſwer: you ſee now how ready I have ſhewed my ſelf to ſatisfie your Demands, ſo that I have done my part; wherefore if this Parliament have not an happy concluſion, the ſin is yours, I am free.</p>
            <p>The King having ended, the Houſes teſtified their joy with a mighty ſhout, and preſently the Bells rung, and Bonefires were kindled all the City over: Nor was the true cauſe ſo diſtinctly known; for many ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended at firſt, that the King had delivered the Duke up to them to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59492:19"/>be ſent to the <hi>Tower;</hi> on which miſpriſion, ſome ſaid the Scaffold on <hi>Tower-hill</hi> was inſtantly pulled down; the People ſaid his Grace ſhould have a new one.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid that the Houſe of Lords made Suit to the King upon this happy accord, That he would be pleaſed to receive into Grace thoſe Lords who were in former disfavour; which he readily yielded unto: And admitted the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> the Earls of <hi>Eſſex, Warwick, Briſtol,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Say</hi> to kiſs his hand.</p>
            <p>The Petition thus granted, the Commiſſions of Loan and Exciſe were inſtantly out-lawed, and at the entreaty of the Houſe of Peers, cancell'd in the Kings preſence.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſecured the faults, they removed the faulty, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon a large Remonſtrance to the King, ripping up the Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances themſelves, and the Authors of them. This Remonſtrance conſiſted of ſix Branches, in ſum theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The danger of Innovation and Alteration in Religion:<note place="margin">The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance.</note> This occaſioned by, 1. The great eſteem and favour many Profeſſors of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion receive at Court. 2. Their publick reſort to Maſs at <hi>Denmark</hi>-houſe, contrary to his Majeſties Anſwer to the Parliaments Petition at <hi>Oxford.</hi> 3. The Letters for ſtay of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt them. Laſtly, The daily growth of the <hi>Arminian</hi>-Faction, favoured and protected by <hi>Neal</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and <hi>Laud</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bath-and-Wells,</hi> whileſt the Orthodox party are ſilenced, or diſcountenanced.</item>
               <item>2. The danger of Innovation and Alteration in Government, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by Billeting of Soldiers, by the Commiſſion of procuring One thouſand <hi>German</hi>-Horſe, and Riders, for the defence of the Kingdom, by a ſtanding-Commiſſion granted to the Duke to be General at Land in times of Peace.</item>
               <item>3. Diſaſters of our Deſigns, as the expedition to the Iſle of <hi>Rhe,</hi> and that lately of <hi>Rochel,</hi> wherein the Engliſh have purchaſed their diſhonour with the waſte of a Million of Treaſure.</item>
               <item>4. The want of Ammunition, occaſioned by the late ſelling away of 36 Laſt of Powder.</item>
               <item>5. The decay of Trade, by the loſs of Three hundred Ships taken by the <hi>Dunkirkers</hi> and Pirates within theſe three laſt years.</item>
               <item>6. The not Guarding the Narrow Seas, whereby his Majeſty hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt loſt the Regality.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Of all which Evils and Dangers, the principal cauſe is the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> his exceſſive power, and abuſe of that power; and therefore they humbly ſubmit it to his Majeſties Wiſdom, whether it can be ſafe for Himſelf, or his Kingdom, that ſo great Power ſhould be truſted in the hands of any one Subject whatſoever.</p>
            <p>This Remonſtrance being finiſhed on <hi>Tueſday June</hi> the <hi>17th,</hi> they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it as an Appendix, with a Bill of Subſidies, to the King in the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queting-houſe;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59492:20"/>who having heard it out, He told them, That he little expected ſuch a Remonſtrance, after he had ſo Graciouſly paſſed the Petition of Right: As for their Grievances, he would conſider of them, as they ſhould deſerve. Some ſay, that at his paſſing out, the King gave the Duke his hand to kiſs, which others only ſuppoſe was no more than the Dukes low congy to his Majeſties hand.</p>
            <p>It is alſo reported, That the King being informed that Mr. <hi>Denzil Hollis</hi> had an hand in this Remonſtrance, he replied in the words of <hi>Julius Caeſar, Et tu Brute,</hi> I wonder at it; for we two were fellow-Revellers in a Maſquerade.</p>
            <p>Three days before this Dr. <hi>Manwaring</hi> was queſtioned for ſome Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious paſſages in two Sermons preached, one before the King, and the other at his own Parochial Church; wherein he aſſerted, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That the Kings Royal Command in impoſing, without common conſent in Parliament, Taxes and Loans, doth ſo far bind the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the Subjects of this Kingdom, that they cannot refuſe the payment of them without peril of Eternal damnation.</item>
               <item>2. That the Authority of Parliament is not neceſſary for the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Aids and Subſidies.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe things being too evident to be denied, and too groſs to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of qualification; his Sentence was,
<list>
                  <item>1. Impriſonment during the pleaſure of the Houſe.</item>
                  <item>2. One thouſand pound Fine to the King.</item>
                  <item>3. To make ſuch ſubmiſſion and acknowledgment of his offence, as ſhall be ſet down by a Committee in Writing, both at the Bar of the Lords Houſe, and at the Houſe of Commons.</item>
                  <item>4. To be ſuſpended for three years from the exerciſe of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry.</item>
                  <item>5. To be diſabled from ever Preaching at Court hereafter.</item>
                  <item>6. To be diſabled for ever from having any Eccleſiaſtical Dignity, or Secular Office.</item>
                  <item>7. That as his Book is worthy to be burnt, ſo his Majeſty may be moved to Grant a Proclamation for the calling of it in; as alſo for the burning of it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>According to the third particular, of which Sentence two days after, he made his ſubmiſſion on his knees.</p>
            <p>Whileſt the Parliament was buſie about this Doctor, the King was as buſie about the late Remonſtrance; to which he formed a formal Anſwer, traverſing and denying all their charge; wherewith the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons being ſomewhat irritated (for it was a ſmart one) fell down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right upon another Remonſtrance againſt Tonnage and Poundage: But the King was unwilling to hear of any more Remonſtrances of that nature, and therefore reſolved to fruſtrate it by Proroguing of the Parliament unto <hi>October</hi> the <hi>20th.</hi> And <hi>June</hi> the 26. 1628, being the laſt of this Seſſion, his Majeſty calling both Houſes together, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Royal Aſſent to the Bills, delivered his mind unto them, as
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59492:20"/>you may read <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>84th</hi> of the aforeſaid Narrative.</p>
            <p>The Parliament being thus Prorogued, the Commons were exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly Male-content; for they deſired only a Receſs and Adjournment, whereby all matters then depending might be found in the ſame ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and condition, as at their next meeting wherein they at preſent left them.</p>
            <p>In this Month Dr. <hi>Lamb,</hi> a creature of the Dukes,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Lamb</hi> his Exemplary Death.</note> commended to him by Biſhop <hi>Williams,</hi> ſuffer'd for the teſtimony of a lewd conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. Having been at a Play-houſe, at his return ſome boys began to affront him, and call him the <hi>Dukes Devil;</hi> whereupon he hired ſome to guard him home; and taking in at a Cooks ſhop, where he ſupt, the people watcht his coming out; but he was ſo ſtrongly guarded, as they durſt not venture on him. Then he went to the <hi>Windmill-Tavern</hi> in <hi>Lothbury;</hi> and at length coming forth, the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult being much increaſed, gave the onſet, and aſſaulted him, ſo as he was forced to take refuge in the next houſe; but the enraged multitude threatned to pull down the houſe, unleſs <hi>Lamb</hi> were ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered unto them: The Maſter of the Houſe was a Lawyer, and fearing ſome ſad conſequence of this uproar, diſcreetly ſends for four Conſtables to guard him out; but the furious multitude flew at him in the midſt of his Auxiliaries, ſtruck him down; and mauled him ſo, as that they beat out one of his eyes, and left him half dead upon the place.</p>
            <p>In this plight he was carried into the Counter in the <hi>Poultrey</hi> (no other houſe being willing to receive him), where the next morning he changed this life either for a better, or for a worſe.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>23d.</hi> following, the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> (by one <hi>John Felton</hi>) was ſtabbed at <hi>Portſmouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Buchingham</hi> Murdered.</note> who being at breakfaſt with <hi>Soubire</hi> and others of principal quality, this <hi>Felton</hi> (ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a Lieutenant to a Foot-Company in the Regiment of Sir <hi>John Ramſey</hi>) who had but about a week before meditated the Act, but had not yet contrived the means, ſneaks into the Chamber vigilantly to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve every opportunity ſerviceable for his purpoſe; and finding the Duke ready to riſe from the Table, he withdraws into an Entry through which the Duke was to paſs, who coming by with Sir <hi>Thomas Fryer</hi> (to whom he declined his ear in the poſture of attention) in the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his retiring from the Duke, <hi>Felton</hi> with a back blow ſtabbed him in the left ſide into the very heart, leaving the Knife, which was a Tenpenny Coutel, in his Body.</p>
            <p>Some now thought, that though his Majeſty diſliked the mode of this great mans diſpatch, yet with the thing he was well enough ſatisfied, as if Providence had thereby rid him of the Subject of his ſo great perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity whom he could not preſerve with ſafety, nor deſert with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; but ſuch as theſe were ſoon convinced of their error, when they obſerved how his Majeſty did treat his relations with ſo intenſe reſpect.</p>
            <p>But whatever ſatisfaction the King received thereby; certain it is, the Common man was well enough pleaſed thereat: For though Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59492:21"/>and the Law found the Act Murder, yet in vulgar ſenſe it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſt for an Executioner of a Malefactor, and an Adminiſtration of that Juſtice, diſpenced from Heaven, which they thought was denied on Earth: And becauſe all thoſe ſtorms, or publick miſcarriages, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in the lower Region of the Parliament, had of late been termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated in him as their grand efficient; every man would now be wiſe, and foreſpeak fair weather and a ſweet harmony between the King and his Subjects; but how truly, a few Months will diſcover.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>November</hi> the <hi>29th, Felton</hi> having been arraigned and found guilty at the <hi>Kings-Bench-Bar,</hi> ſuffered at <hi>Tyburn:</hi> His Confeſſion was as ſincere, and full of remorſe as could be wiſhed; the fact he much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, and renounced his former error in conceiving it would be for his glory to ſacrifice himſelf for his Countreys good. And whereas other Motives were ſuggeſted by report, he proteſted upon his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he had no other inducement thereunto, than the Parliaments Remonſtrance. His body was from thence tranſmitted to <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and there hung in Chains.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>January</hi> the <hi>26th,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment meet.</note> 1628, the Parliament meet again, who ſoon found they were like to have work enough; for Complaints came thronging in, eſpecially againſt the Cuſtomers, for taking and diſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Merchants Goods for Tonnage and Poundage; which the King taking notice of, called them to the Banqueting-houſe, and told them, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>That the occaſion of that Meeting, was a complaint made in the lower Houſe, for ſtaying of ſome mens Goods, for denying Tonnage and Poundage; which difference might be ſoon decided, were his words and actions rightly underſtood: For if he did not take thoſe Duties as an Appendix of his Hereditary Prerogative, and had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared he challeng'd them not of right, and only deſired to enjoy them by the gift of his People; Why did they not paſs the Bill, as they promiſed to him, to clear his by-paſt actions and future proceedings, eſpecially in this his time of ſo great neceſſity.</p>
               <p>Therefore he did now expect they ſhould make good what they promiſed, and put an end to all queſtions emergent from their delay.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The Houſe of Commons ſaid, That Religion is above Policy, God above the King; and that they intend to reform Religion, before they engage in any other conſideration: Nor was it agreeable to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſultation, to have their Tranſactions proſcribed; ſo that they would at preſent lay aſide the Bill of Tonnage and Poundage, till they thought convenient: and they were as good as their words. For the firſt thing they reſolved upon, was the appointment of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees (which the Courtiers called an Inquiſition), one for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, another for Civil Affairs; and theſe to repreſent the abuſes in both.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:59492:21"/>
The Abuſes then in the Church, and likewiſe in the State, as repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Commons by their Committees, you may read at large, <hi>Page</hi> 97, 98, 99, 100, 101. in the ſaid Narrative.</p>
            <p>But the diſtempers continued ſo long, and with ſo quick and high a pulſe, as the King having every day notice of them, He forthwith ſent for the Serjeant of the Mace, but the Houſe would not permit him to depart; but taking the key of the door from him, gave it to Sir <hi>Miles Hobart,</hi> a Member of the Houſe, to keep: The King deeply incenſed at theſe Exceedings of contempt, ſent <hi>Maxwell,</hi> Uſher of the Black Rod, to Diſſolve the Parliament; but neither he nor his Meſſage would be admitted: Whereupon the King, much enraged, ſent for the Captain of the Penſioners, and the Guard, to force an entrance: But this paſſion that ſhut out the King, yet let ſo much reaſon in, as perſwaded them it was good ſleeping in a whole skin; and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Kings intentions, they ſuddenly voided the Houſe.</p>
            <p>Soon after this, the King came that very morning into the Houſe of Lords, and making a ſhort (though ſmart) Speech unto them, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Lord-Keeper to Diſſolve that Parliament.</p>
            <p>The King having thus Diſſolved this Parliament,<note place="margin">The King ſends forth a Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> or rather broke up School, thoſe whom he now called <hi>Vipers,</hi> had not in the Houſe of Commons ſpit up all their Malignity, but reſerv'd ſome to diſperſe and diſpoſe of in the Country, whereby an ill odour might be caſt upon his Government, and the hearts of his People alienated from him. As an antidote therefore againſt that poyſon, and to anticipate all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding, he ſpeedeth out a Declaration, ſetting forth to all his Subjects the Motives perſwading him to Diſſolve the Parliament, and a breviate of all the Tranſactions in this and the former Seſſion; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, minding them in the cloſe of all, that the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> was decried while he lived, as the ſolitary cauſe of all bad events in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Parliaments; that he is dead, and yet the Diſtempers not in the leaſt abated, which he takes as an argument that they were miſtaken in the cauſe; and, that it was rather reſident in ſome few Members of Parliament.</p>
            <p>The King having, as he hoped, diſabuſed his Subjects by his late Declaration; next intended to proceed ſeverely againſt thoſe who had offended him, and whoſe puniſhment he ſaid he reſerved to a due time upon this account; the <hi>18th</hi> of this Month he ſent for Ten of the late Members to appear at the Council-Table, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> Sir <hi>Miles Hobart,</hi> Sir <hi>John Elliot,</hi> Sir <hi>Peter Hayman,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stroud,</hi> Mr. <hi>Coriton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Valentine,</hi> Mr. <hi>Long,</hi> Mr. <hi>Kirton:</hi> Theſe appearing, Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> was interrogated, Wherefore (contrary to his former uſe) he did the morning the Parliament was Diſſolved, place himſelf by the Chair, above divers of the Privy-Councellors?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:59492:22"/>
He anſwered, That he had ſome other times as well as then, ſeated himſelf in that place; and as for his ſitting above the Privy-Councellors, he took it to be his due in any place whatſoever (unleſs at the Council-Board); and for his part, he came into the Houſe with as much zeal for his Majeſties Service, as any one whatſoever; and yet nevertheleſs find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Majeſty was offended with him, he humbly deſired that he might rather be the ſubject of his mercy, than of his power. To the which the Lord Treaſurer anſwered, You mean rather of his Majeſties Mercy than of his Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> replyed, I ſay of his Majeſties Power, my Lord.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Elliot</hi> was next called in, who was queſtioned for words he ſpake in the lower Houſe of Parliament, and for producing the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance.</p>
            <p>To this he anſwered,</p>
            <p>That whatſoever was ſaid or done by him in that place, and at that time, was performed by him as a publick Man, and a Member of that Houſe, and that he was and ever will be ready to give an account of his Sayings and Doings in that place, whenever he ſhould be called unto it by that Houſe; where (as he taketh it) he is only to be queſtioned; and in the mean time being now but a private man, he would not now trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelf to remember what he ſaid or did in that place, as a publick Man.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Miles Hobart</hi> was alſo queſtioned for locking the Parliament Houſe Door, and putting the Key in his Pocket; to which he pleaded the Command of the Houſe.</p>
            <p>The other Gentlemen were queſtioned for reproving the Speaker, and not permitting him to do that the King commanded him, who all alledged in defence the Priviledg of the Houſe.</p>
            <p>After this they were committed ſome to the Tower, and ſome to the Gatehouſe, and ſome to the Fleet: And <hi>May</hi> the firſt, the Attorney ſent a Proceſs out againſt them to appear in the Star-Chamber, and to anſwer an information to be entred there againſt them; but they refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as denying the Juriſdiction of that Court over offences done in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, which created the greateſt and longeſt Controverſie in Law that had been ſtarted in many years.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> the tenth,<note place="margin">Anno Domini, <hi>1630,</hi>
               </note> dyed <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> Lord High Steward of <hi>England,</hi> of an Apoplexy.</p>
            <p>He was the very Picture and <hi>vive Effigies</hi> of Nobility;<note place="margin">His Character</note> His Perſon ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Majeſtick than Elegant; his preſence whether quiet or in motion,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59492:22"/>full of ſtately gravity; his mind generous and purely heroick; often ſtout, but never diſloyal; ſo vehement an opponent of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> as when that Match fell under conſideration, he would ſometimes rowze even to the trepidation of King <hi>James,</hi> yet kept in favour ſtill; for that King knew well enough that plain dealing was a Jewel in all men, ſo in a Privy Councellor was an ornamental duty; and the ſame true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartedneſs commended him to King <hi>Charles,</hi> with whom he kept a moſt admirable Correſpondence, and yet ſtood the firm confident of the Commonalty, and not by a ſneaking cunning, but by an erect and generous prudence, ſuch as rendred him unſuſpected of Ambition on the one ſide, or of Faction on the other.</p>
            <p>This univerſality of Affection made his loſs moſt deplorable, but men are loſt when all turns to forgotten-duſt: That affection would not that he ſhould be ſo nonpluſs'd, but kept his noble Fame emergent and aloſe, and if this Hiſtory ſhall bear it up, I ſhall eſteem it not more his felicity than my own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> the twenty fifth of this year, was Arraigned, Convicted,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1631.</note> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and on <hi>May</hi> the fourteenth Executed upon <hi>Tower-Hill, Mervin</hi> Lord <hi>Audley,</hi> Earl of <hi>Caſtle-Haven,</hi> for Rape and Sodomy.</p>
            <p>In <hi>England</hi> fell two great Favourites of different parties,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1634.</note> of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalties one, and of the Kings another: Of the Commonalties, Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> who died about the latter end of this Summer;<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this life.</note> full of days he died, moſt whereof he had ſpent in eminent place and honour. His abilities in the Common Law, whereof he paſſed for an Oracle, raiſed him firſt to the dignity of Attorney-General to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Then of Lord Chief Juſtice of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> under King <hi>James:</hi> His advancement he loſt the ſame way he got it, <hi>viz.</hi> by his Tongue, ſo rare it is for a man very eloquent, not to be over loquent; long lived he in that retirement, to which Court-Indignation had remitted him, yet was not his receſs inglorious, for at improving a diſgrace to the beſt advantage, he was ſo excellent; as King <hi>James</hi> ſaid of him, he was like a Cat, throw her which way you will ſhe will light upon her feet. And finding a Cloud at Court, he made ſure of fair weather in the Country, applying himſelf ſo devoutly to popular Intereſts, as in ſucceeding Parliaments the Prerogative felt him as her ableſt, ſo her moſt active Opponent; upon which account he was 1 <hi>Caroli</hi> made High Sheriff of <hi>Buckinghamſhire,</hi> on purpoſe to exclude him the enſuing Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; there being an eſpecial <hi>Nolumus</hi> and clauſe in his Commiſſion, prohibiting his Election; not withſtanding which Elected he was in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and thoſe words of Reſtraint upon the debate of the Queſtion in the Houſe of Commons, Voted void.</p>
            <p>On the Kings, the Great Lord Treaſurer Sir <hi>Richard Weſton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Richard Weſton</hi> Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> dieth.</note> Earl of <hi>Portland,</hi> this year and he almoſt expiring together, he ending this life <hi>March</hi> the thirteenth, a ſad loſs to the King, and the ſadder becauſe he
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59492:23"/>thought it irreparable. The truth is, he was a Perſon very able for the Office, and the Exchequer was in the mending hand, while he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed that place; for he had a moſt ſingular Artifice, both in improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the incomes, and in a frugal moderation of his Maſters expence. But the Kings forrow was not ſo extreme for him, but the Peoples joy was full as great; for there was now grown ſo ſad an antipathy between his Majeſty and his Subjects, that like thoſe two Emperors, <hi>Antonine</hi> and <hi>Geta,</hi> they were always of contrary Senſes and Minds, rarely agreeing in any one particular. The deportment whereby he ſo much diſobliged the Commonalty, was his promoting Monopolies and other advantages of Regality.</p>
            <p>The Archbiſhop and he were uſually at great odds; this vacant place was at preſent entruſted to Commiſſioners, until the King ſhould otherwiſe diſpoſe thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>September</hi> the <hi>29th,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Arundel</hi> brought up to <hi>London,</hi> out of <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> one <hi>Robert Parr,</hi> as the wonder of our times for long life, he having attained to the age of near 160; and probably might have continued longer, had not ſo tedious a journey and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violent agitation of his aged Body accellerated his end; ſo that it may be ſaid, he ſacrificed ſome years to others curioſity.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Michaelmas</hi>-Term was canvaſſed and debated the grand Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie between the King and Subject about Ship-Money;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1635. The great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate about Ship-money.</note> for the Ship-Writs having been iſſued out <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 11, to divers Counties, many Inhabitants, and among the reſt Mr. <hi>Hambden</hi> of <hi>Buckingham-ſhire,</hi> aſſeſſed by the Sheriff, made default of payment; whereupon the King, equally hating to be either flattered into, or frighted from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of its Legality, wrote a Letter to the Judges, demanding their Opinions upon the caſe ſtated.</p>
            <p>To which the Judges delivered their Opinions as followeth:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="opinions">
               <body>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:59492:23"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe your moſt Excellent Majeſty,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WE have, according to your Majeſties Command, ſeverally, and every Man by himſelf, and all of us together, taken into our ſerious conſideration the Caſe and Queſtions ſigned by your Majeſty, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed in your Letter. And we are of opinion, That when the good and ſafety of the Kingdom in general is concerned, and the whole Kingdom in danger, Your Majeſty may by Writ under your Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> Command all the Subjects of this your Kingdom, at their charge to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide and furniſh ſuch number of Ships with Men, Victual, Munition, and for ſuch time as your Majeſty ſhall think fit, for the defence and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of the Kingdom from ſuch peril and danger: and that by Law your Majeſty may compel the doing thereof in caſe of refulſal or refracto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs. And we are alſo of opinion, That in ſuch caſe your Majeſty is the ſole Judg, both of the danger, and when and how the ſame is to be prevented and avoided.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Bramſton,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Finch,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Humphrey Davenport,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Denham,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Hatton,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Jones,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Crook,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Trever,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Vernon,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Barkley,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Francis Crauly,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Weſton.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Theſe Opinions being ſubſcribed by all the Judges, and inrolled in all the Courts in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-Hall, the King thought he had now warrant ſufficient to proceed againſt all defaulters, and eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Mr. <hi>Hambden;</hi> who being ſummoned by proceſs, appeared and required <hi>Oyer</hi> of the Ship-Writs; which being read, he demurred in Law, and demanded the Opinion of all the Judges upon the Legal ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of thoſe Writs.</p>
            <p>This great Caſe coming to be argued in the Exchequer, the Major part of the Judges delivered their Opinions in favour of the Writs, and accordingly gave Judgment againſt Mr. <hi>Hambden;</hi> yet did not the queſtion altogether ſo repoſe; but Mr. <hi>Hambden</hi> obſerving ſome Judges, <hi>viz. Crook</hi> and <hi>Hatton</hi> of a contrary ſenſe, held up the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſtill, though all in vain; all his inquietude not gaining him the leaſt acquittal, until an higher Power interpoſed.</p>
            <p>About the beginning of <hi>January,</hi> this year,<note place="margin">Anno <hi>1639. Sir</hi> Thomas Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry <hi>dyeth:</hi>
               </note> dyed Sir <hi>Thomas Coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> Lord-Keeper of the Great Seal of <hi>England;</hi> a Dignity he had Fifteen years enjoyed; if it be not more proper to ſay, That Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity had enjoyed him ſo long; this latter affording not one every way of more apt qualifications for the place: His front and preſence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpake a venerable regard, not inferior to that of any of his Anceſtors: His train and ſuit of followers was diſpoſed agreeably to ſhun both envy and contempt; not like that of the Viſcount St. <hi>Albans,</hi> or the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> whom he ſucceeded, ambitious and vain: His port
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59492:24"/>was State, theirs Oſtentation; they were indeed the more knowng men, but their Learning was extravagant to their Office; of what concerned his Place he knew well enough, and which is the main, act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to his knowledg; for in the adminiſtration of Juſtice, he was ſo erect and ſo incorrupt, as captious malice ſtands mute in the blemiſh of his fame; a miracle the greater, when we conſider that he was alſo a Privy Councellor: A Truſt wherein he ſerved his Maſter the King moſt faithfully, and the more faithfully, becauſe of all thoſe Councils which in thoſe times did ſo much deceive his Majeſty, (and I pray God there were fewer at this juncture of time than there is) he was an earneſt diſſwader, and did much diſaffect thoſe Sticklers, who rather laboured to make the Prerogative tall and great, as knowing that ſuch men loved the King better than <hi>Charles Stuart:</hi> ſo that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he was a Courtier, and had for his Maſter a paſſion moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe, yet had he alſo always, of paſſion, ſome reſerve for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick welfare.</p>
            <p>An Argument of a free, noble, and right principled mind; for what both Court and Country have always held as inconſiſtent, is in truth erroneous; and no man can be truly Loyal, who is not alſo a good Patriot, nor any a good Patriot, (the Ballance indiſpenſably ought to be kept even) who is not truly Loyal.</p>
            <p>To this worthy Gentleman ſucceeded Sir <hi>John Finch,</hi> formerly Lord Chief Juſtice of the Common Pleas.</p>
            <p>The Heer <hi>Somerdick,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor from the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> Embaſſador from the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> in the Month of <hi>January</hi> had Audience of the King: He had with him Count <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> and the <hi>Rhine-Grave,</hi> with a very ſplendid train; his buſineſs was to give his Majeſty ſatisfaction concerning the late At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack made upon the <hi>Spaniards</hi> by the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet in the <hi>Downs,</hi> and the Embaſſy was ſweetned by ſome overture of Marriage between the young Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and the Kings Eldeſt Daughter.</p>
            <p>On the Thirteenth of <hi>April,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Parliament fits in <hi>England</hi> after near 12 years inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, <hi>April</hi> 1640.</note> A Parliament met and ſate, and the Deputy of <hi>Ireland</hi> being not long before Created Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and made Lord Lieutenant of that Kingdom, was lead into the upper Houſe by two Noblemen, where he gave an account of his ſervice in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where he had obtained the grant of four Subſidies for the maintenance of an Army.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>John Glanvil</hi> was choſen Speaker of the Houſe of Commons, and generally the choice of Members to that Houſe was ſo good, that great probabilitles were given of a happy Union betwixt the King and the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Some few days after, a Report was made to the Lords, by the Lord <hi>Cottington,</hi> (who with <hi>Windebank</hi> and the Attorney General, were ſent
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59492:24"/>by the King to the Lord <hi>Lowden,</hi> to examine him concerning a Letter before mentioned) that the Lord did acknowledge the Hand-Writing to be his, and that it was framed before the pacification at <hi>Berwick,</hi> and was never ſent to the King, but only prepared in a readineſs, ſhould need require; and that it was ſuppreſt upon that pacificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; nevertheleſs it was thought fit he ſhould continue in the ſame ſtate, until clearer Evidence ſhould be given either for or againſt him.</p>
            <p>Soon after the King ſent a meſſage to the Lower Houſe about Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, repreſenting unto them the intolerable indignities and injuries wherewith the <hi>Scots</hi> had treated him; and withal declared unto them, that if they would aſſiſt him ſutable to the exigency of his ſad oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, he would for ever quit his claim of Shipmoney, and into the bargain give them full content in all their juſt demands.</p>
            <p>But they replied (as being ſomewhat deliberate in this affair of Money) that they expected firſt ſecurity from his Majeſty in theſe three particulars, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>For the clearing the Subjects Property.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>For the Eſtabliſhment of Religion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>For the Priviledg of Parliament.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Many Conferences there was had between the Lords and Commons, as to this old Conteſt, which ſhould precede: The Lords after a ſtrong diviſion among themſelves, at length Voted for the King, and the Commons for the Subject. But it was not long before this unhappy differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was unhappily decided: For Secretary <hi>Vane</hi> who was employed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the particulars of the Kings deſires, required twelve Subſidies, whereas it was ſaid his expreſs order was for only ſix; ſome there are who ſuſpect this miſtake to have been not involuntary, but indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious in him as to his Majeſties ſervice; but leaving that undeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, the Houſe of Commons was raiſed by this Propoſition, to ſuch animoſity, as the King adviſing with his <hi>Juncto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment diſſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>May</hi> the fifth, 1640. having ſate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 3 weeks.</note> their complyance was repreſented to him ſo deſperate, as that <hi>May</hi> the fifth he ordered the Diſſolution of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Thus expired this ſhort-liv'd, or rather thus ended this ſtill-born Parliament, (although we have had a much ſhorter, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1680.) A Parliament, I know not whether more unfortunate in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning ſo late, or ending ſo ſoon: A Parliament which had Power (and probably Will) enough to impede the torrent of the late Civil War; for the breaches between the King and People were grown ſo high, as one might already diſcern all the lineaments of an Inſurrection in <hi>Embrio</hi> (but by my Authors good leave, the wiſeſt head could not foreſee contingent actions; for who could foretel but that his late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty might have been adviſed by his Grand Council, and not by his
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59492:25"/>Court Favourites) whoſe abortion nothing could cauſe but a happy u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in Parliament, a thing not very difficult, much leſs impoſſible at that time, had the King yielded to a detrenching ſome luxuriances of his Prerogative, to the reducing Epiſcopacy to its primitive inſtitution, that is, to the frame by Divine Right (a Root which had not ſap enough to maintain ſo ſpreading and flouriſhing a Top as was contended for) to a more frequent and ſociable communication with the grand Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. In ſhort, ſo much fluent and ſpontaneous conceſſions as being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon too late, were (in reference to his perſonal ſecurity) loſt and thrown away in the enſuing Parliament, of the which we ſhall now very ſuddenly come to give a very ſuccinct account as to their particular proceedings and tranſactions, and compare both theſe Parliaments to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with thoſe that have been aſſembled of late, <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 1680. and 1681. And after that ſhall draw towards a concluſion, as I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it will be high time, leſt my <hi>Multum in Parvo &amp; Vox Veritatis,</hi> ſhould prove at the long run, <hi>Vox Contractitionis.</hi> But this only by the way.</p>
            <p>And moreover the diſſolution of this Parliament was aſcribed (tho' perhaps wrongfully) to the advice of the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Archbiſhop <hi>Laud</hi> beſet by the Rabble, in his Houſe at <hi>Lambeth.</hi>
               </note> ſo that on the ninth of <hi>May</hi> a Paper was poſted upon the Old Exchange, by one <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> exciting the Apprentices to riſe and rifle his Houſe at <hi>Lambeth</hi> on <hi>Monday</hi> following; of which he having notice, made proviſion againſt them for his own defence; and many of them upon enquiry, having been actors therein, were apprehended and impriſon'd in the White Lyon in <hi>Southwark,</hi> but within three days after ſome of their Complices got together, and came to the Priſon and brake it open and ſet them free; yet nevertheleſs one of the chief Ringleaders was Taken, Arraigned, Condemned, and Drawn, Hanged, and Quartered, on the 21 of <hi>May.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Convention was not more unhappily diſſolved,<note place="margin">The Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſitteth.</note> than another was continued, that is, as a witty Gentleman ſaid well, A new Synod made of an old Convocation; which by new Commiſſions from the King, were impowered to ſit ſtill, the Impulſives to it are very eaſily collected from what reſulted from it, as you read more at large in the aforeſaid Author, <hi>Pápe</hi> 189.</p>
            <p>The Parliament being blown away without affording any thing in nature of a ſupply to the Kings wants: All the wheels of the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive are put into motion, to carry on the War againſt <hi>Scotland:</hi> Firſt, the City of <hi>London</hi> were invited to a Loan; then all Knights and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, who held Lands in <hi>Capite</hi> of the King, were ſummoned to ſend Men, Horſes, and Arms, agreeable to their abilities.</p>
            <p>In <hi>September,</hi> the Lords <hi>Mandevil</hi> and <hi>Edward Howard,</hi> delivered to the King, at <hi>York,</hi> this Petition.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:59492:25"/>
                  <head>To the King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The humble Petition of Your Majeſties moſt Loyal and moſt Obedient Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, whoſe names are underwritten, in behalf of themſelves and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt Gracious Soveraign,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Zeal of that Duty and Service which we owe to your Sacred Majeſty, and our earneſt affections to the good and welfare of this your Realm of <hi>England,</hi> have moved us in all humility to beſeech your Royal Majeſty, to give us leave to offer to your Princely wiſdom the apprehenſion which we and others your faithful Subjects have concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the great diſtempers and dangers, now threatning the Church and State, and your Royal Perſon, and of the fitteſt means by which they may be removed and prevented.</p>
                  <p>The evils and dangers which your Majeſty may be pleaſed to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. <hi>That your Majeſties Sacred Perſon is expoſed to hazard and danger in the preſent Expedition againſt the</hi> Scotiſh <hi>Army, and by occaſion of this War, Your Majeſties Revenue is much waſted, your Subjects (with Coat and conduct Money, Billetting of Souldiers, and other Military Charges, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Rapines and Diſorders committed in ſeveral parts of this your Realm, by the Souldiers raiſed for that Service) and your whole Kingdom become full of fears and diſcontents.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>The ſundry innovations in matter of Religion, the Oath and Canons lately impoſed upon the Clergy, and other your Majeſties Subjects.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. <hi>The great increaſe of Popery, and the Employing of Popiſh Recuſants, and others ill affected to the Religion by Laws Eſtabliſhed, in places of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Truſt, eſpecially in commanding of Men and Arms both in the Field and ſundry Counties of this your Realm; whereas by Law they are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to have any Arms in their own Houſes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>IV. <hi>The great miſchiefs which may fall upon this Kingdom, if the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions which have been credibly reported of bringing in Iriſh and Foreign Forces ſhould take effect.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>V. <hi>The urging of Ship-money, and proſecution of ſome Sheriffs in the Star-Chamber for not levying of it.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>VI. <hi>The heavy charge upon Merchandize, to the diſcouragement of Trade, the multitude of Monopolies and other Patents, whereby the Commodities and Manufactures of the Kingdom are much burthened, to the great and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal grievance of your People.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>VII. <hi>The great grief of your People and Subjects, by long intermiſſion of Parliaments, and the late and former Diſſolving of ſuch as have been called, without the happy effects which otherwiſe they might have produced.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>For remedy whereof, and prevention of the Dangers that may ariſe to your Royal Perſon and to the whole State, they do in all humility and faithfulneſs beſeech your Moſt Excellent Majeſty, that you would
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59492:26"/>be pleaſed to Summon a Parliament within ſome convenient time, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the cauſes of theſe and other great Grievances, which your People lie under, may be taken away, and the Authors and Counſellors of them may be brought to ſuch legal and condign puniſhment as the nature of their ſeveral offences ſhall require; And that the preſent War may be compoſed by your Majeſty's wiſdom, without Blood, in ſuch manner as may conduce to the Honour and Safety of your Majeſties Perſon, the the comfort of your People, and the uniting of both your Realms againſt the Common Enemy of the Reformed Religion.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>And your Majeſty's Petitioners ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Francis Bedford</item>
                           <item>Robert Eſſex</item>
                           <item>Mulgrave</item>
                           <item>Say and Seal</item>
                           <item>Edward Howard</item>
                           <item>William Hartford</item>
                           <item>Warwick</item>
                           <item>Bullingbrooke</item>
                           <item>Mandevil</item>
                           <item>Brook</item>
                           <item>Paget</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Concluded the 28th of</hi> Auguſt. 1640.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="answer">
               <body>
                  <head>The King's Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>BEfore the receipt of your Petition, His Majeſty well foreſaw the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that threatens himſelf and Crown, and therefore reſolved the <hi>24th</hi> of this Inſtant, to Summon all the Peers, and with them to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, what in this Caſe is fitteſt to be done for his own honour and fafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Kingdom, where they with the reſt may offer any thing that may conduce to thoſe ends.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>According to this Reſolution, the Lord-Keeper had Directions from the King to iſſue out Writs of Summons for their appearing at <hi>York</hi> on the day prefixt, which he punctually purſued.</p>
            <p>Soon after the preſenting of this Petition from the Lords, came ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the <hi>Scots,</hi> the ſubſtance whereof was a Deſire, That His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty would call a Parliament, for ſetling a firm peace between the two Nations.</p>
            <p>To this Petition the King replyed, with ſignification of what he had ordered before, in reference to himſelf and to the welfare of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
            <p>And the Truth of it is, it was high time for an Accommodation to be effected; for <hi>Leſley</hi> now began to rant it in <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> and the parts adjacent, as <hi>Brennus</hi> did at <hi>Rome,</hi> with a <hi>Vae Victis:</hi> He impoſed a Tax of 350 pounds <hi>per diem</hi> upon the Biſhoprick of <hi>Durham;</hi> and 300 pounds upon <hi>Northumberland,</hi> upon pain of Plundering; and yet permitted Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to rifle Houſes, break open Shops, and act what inſolencies they pleaſed; ſeized upon four great <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships laden with Corn, as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful prize, they not knowing in whoſe poſſeſſion the Town was till they enter'd the Haven.</p>
            <p>The firſt day of the Lords Aſſembling at <hi>York,</hi> it was reſolved that a Parliament ſhould be Summoned to convene at <hi>Weſtminſter, November</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:59492:26"/>the Third. Then a Meſſage was ſent to the <hi>Scots,</hi> deſiring a ſpeedy Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at <hi>York.</hi> The <hi>Scots</hi> replied, They held that no place of ſecurity for their Commiſſioners, conſidering that the Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who commanded His Majeſties Army, was one who had proclaimed them Traytors in <hi>Ireland,</hi> before the King had done the ſame in <hi>England,</hi> and who had threatned to deſtroy their Nation both Root and Branch, and againſt whom, as a chief Incendiary of the late Troubles, they intended to complain; whereupon it was concluded, that the Treaty ſhould be held at <hi>Rippon,</hi> which accordingly took place.</p>
            <p>The Parliament now approaching, whoſe Convening was attended by this Kingdom with ſo much longing, ſuch impatience of deſires, as every moment which retarded it, was interpreted as a kind of Grievance to the Subject; for we began now to think, that nothing could make us a happy People but a Parliament, and that no Parliament could make us miſerable. This was the Sence of the greater part of this Nation; and if this Parliament ſucceeded not adequate to ſome Mens Vote, perhaps the miſcarriage of their hopes may be ſomewhat imputed to this Sence; Over-ruling Providence delights oft to order the Operations of free and natural Agents, counter to Mans Expectations, to teach us the vanity of that Faith which is founded upon Cauſes ſubaltern.</p>
            <p>And oh! that I could here but expreſs to the life, the high Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the People from this Parliament, which came with ſuch a terrible ſwing, after ſo long an Interval, and ſo many Diſſolutions, that put the whole Nation into ſuch a Conſternation, as, I preſume, the like Preſident cannot be produced out of the Records of Antiquity, ſince <hi>William the Conqueror</hi> did firſt invade our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Territories.</p>
            <p>But however (Courteous Readers) for your preſent Divertiſement, I will here make a ſmall Attempt, to expreſs the preſent Thoughts and Expectations of that Parliament, which in proceſs of time brake forth into a Civil War, (and I pray God I may never live to ſee the like again) the which I ſhall repreſent under the Emblem of a new, tight, and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built Ship, which upon the Launching, was named, <hi>The Bon Reſolution,</hi> (although ſome would have it called, <hi>The Houſe of Commons,</hi> others, <hi>The Three Eſtates,</hi> and others, <hi>The Swiftſure</hi>) and was immediately employ'd in His Majeſties Service, but being for ſome time wind-bound within the Harbor, (<hi>viz.</hi> about 12 days) the Captain of the ſaid Ship coming early out of his Cabin one morning, and finding the Wind tackt about, and blowing fair for his intended Voyage, being upon the Quarter-Deck, he knocks up his Seamen, and ſalutes them after this manner: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>ARiſe you Mortals, from your Dens of Sleep,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neptune</hi> now calls, to launch into the Deep,</l>
               <l>The Wind blows fair, it's lately turn'd South-weſt,</l>
               <l>And we muſt Sail directly to the Eaſt:</l>
               <l>For Pearls and Diamonds, Jewels of great Rate,</l>
               <l>Which in the Acqueſt, ſometimes a broken Pate</l>
               <l>Hath been our Lot; yet ſtill we venture must,</l>
               <l>You know our Shipwrights (wherein ſo great a Trust</l>
               <l>Is now repos'd in us, comes from <hi>Whitehall</hi>)</l>
               <l>Our late Commiſſion; whence we may learn All</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:59492:27"/>
Which way to ſteer our courſe, and will direct</l>
               <l>Whom we muſt cruſh; and whom we must protect</l>
               <l>In this our Voyage. 'Tis the Common-weal</l>
               <l>Of theſe Three Kingdoms, That a Roaring Peal</l>
               <l>Of Small and Great Shot now aloud must Ring</l>
               <l>From this our Veſſel. To preſerve the King</l>
               <l>In all His Legal Rights. But to advance</l>
               <l>Againſt all thoſe, who have lead up a Dance,</l>
               <l>As will, in time, if Heavens do not prevent,</l>
               <l>Deſtroy both King, and all the Parliament,</l>
               <l>And in their ſtead ſet up a Scarlet Whore,</l>
               <l>Of whoſe ſweet Nature we have long before</l>
               <l>Known by Experience, and now for to be cheated</l>
               <l>By their Sham-Plots again, and to be defeated,</l>
               <l>Huzza, Brave Lads! This thing ſhall never be,</l>
               <l>We'll rather chuſe upon a Triple Tree</l>
               <l>To take our chance, and now Heavens crown the Event,</l>
               <l>And bleſs our Veſſel, and our good Intent;</l>
               <l>Heavens bleſs us from the <hi>Sally</hi> Men of War,</l>
               <l>Heavens bleſs us likewiſe that we do not jar</l>
               <l>Among our ſelves. If ſuch a thing ſhould be,</l>
               <l>And that our Seamen now ſhould diſagree,</l>
               <l>And fight for Thimbles, Bodkins, and Gu-gaws,</l>
               <l>Inſtead of fighting for the Good Old Cauſe</l>
               <l>Of Liberty and Property. Oh! this Evil</l>
               <l>Would make us Zealots for the Pope and Devil,</l>
               <l>More than for Chriſts true Church, which now doth ſtand</l>
               <l>In danger much, if theſe ſhould have Command</l>
               <l>Within our <hi>Britiſh</hi> Iſle; which to prevent,</l>
               <l>God bleſs our King, and His next Parliament,</l>
               <l>Which now approacheth, whom we must defend.</l>
               <l>And ſo our Ship, the Lord Almighty ſend</l>
               <l>Into ſafe Harbor, when that we ſhall bring</l>
               <l>Peace to the Church, and Honor to the King;</l>
               <l>And when our Pearls and Diamonds ſhall arrive,</l>
               <l>We'll fix them fast upon King <hi>CHARLES</hi> his Hive,</l>
               <l>His Crown ſhall gliſter like the Riſing Sun.</l>
               <l>Courage, Brave Boys! Our Wars ſhall then be done,</l>
               <l>When we ſhall ſee thoſe Fellows ſent from hence,</l>
               <l>With all their <hi>Tories,</hi> to that place from whence</l>
               <l>They first did riſe, which was from that Grand Syre,</l>
               <l>Who claims the Patent, to be the great Lyar</l>
               <l>And Forger of all Miſchiefs, both in Church and State;</l>
               <l>But will, at length, get ſuch a Broken Pate</l>
               <l>As will confound him, and his Holy Church,</l>
               <l>When as Old Nick ſhall leave him in the Lurch:</l>
               <l>To him I'll leave him, and his Tory Crew,</l>
               <l>And now proceed to what doth here enſue.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:59492:27"/>
               <hi>Tueſday, Novemb.</hi> 3. being the day prefixt, and the Parliament aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, His Majeſty beſpake them in theſe words:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lords,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE knowledge that I have of the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Subjects, was the cauſe of my calling of the laſt Aſſembly of Parliament, wherein if I had been believed, I do most ſincerely think, that things had not fallen as We now ſee; but it is no wonder that men are ſo ſlow to believe, that ſo great a Sedition ſhould be raiſed upon ſo little ground.</p>
                  <p>But now (My Lords and Gentlemen) the Honor and Safety of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom lying ſo heavily at ſtake, I am reſolved to put My Self freely upon the Love and Affections of my <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects,<note place="margin">And had His Majeſty kept cloſe to this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, ſome think things had ne'er come to that extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they did.</note> as thoſe of my Lords that waited upon me at <hi>York,</hi> very well remember, I there declared.</p>
                  <p>Therefor (my Lords) I ſhall not mention Mine own Interest, or that Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port I might juſtly expect from you, till the Common Safety be ſecured; though I must tell you, I am not aſbamed to ſay, thoſe Charges I have been at, have been meerly for the ſecuring the good of this Kingdom, though the Succeſs hath not been anſwerable to My deſires: Therefore I ſhall only deſire you to conſider the best way for the Security of this Kingdom, wherein there are two things chiefly conſiderable:
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1. The chaſing out the Rebells.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2. That other in ſatisfying your juſt Grievances, wherein I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote you to concur ſo heartily and clearly with you, that all the World may ſee my intentions have ever been and ſhall be to make this a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and flouriſhing Kingdom.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are onely two things more that I ſhall mention to you, the one is to tell you, That the Loan of Money which I lately had from the City of <hi>London,</hi> wherein the Lords that waited on me at <hi>York</hi> aſſiſted me, will only maintain my Army for two months, from the beginning of that time it was granted. Now <hi>(my Lords and Gentlemen)</hi> I leave it to your Conſideration, what Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour and Miſchief it might be, in caſe for want of Money my Army be Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded before the Rebels be put out of this Kingdom. Secondly, The ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Calamities the Northern People endure at this time, and ſo long as the Treaty is on foot: And in this I may ſay, Not only they, but all this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom will ſuffer the harm; therefore I leave this alſo to your Conſideration, for the ordering of the Great Affairs whereof, you are to Treat at this time. I am ſo confident of your Love to me, and that your Care is ſuch for the Honour and Safety of the Kingdom, that I ſhould freely leave to you where to begin. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, that you may know the better the State of all Affairs, I have comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my Lord Keeper to give you a ſhort and free Account of thoſe things that have happened in this Interim, with this Proteſtation, <hi>That if his Account be not Satisfactory, as it ought to be, I ſhall, whenſoever you deſire it, give you a Full and Perfect Account of every Particular.</hi> One thing more I deſire of you, as one of the greateſt means to make this an Happy Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That you on your part, as I on mine, lay aſide Suſpition one of another, as I promiſed my Lords at <hi>York;</hi> It ſhall not be my Fault, if this be not a Happy and Good Parliament.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The King having ended, the Lord Keeper, in purſuance of His Majeſty's Commands, gave them a Summary Account and Relation of all Things
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59492:28"/>relating to the Scottiſh Invaſion, I dare not ſay <hi>Rebellion;</hi> for, that the King repreſented them under that Diſguſtful Character, was very ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by ſome conſiderable Peers; whereof His Majeſty having notice, told the Parliament two days after, <hi>He muſt needs call them Rebels, ſo long as they have an Army that does invade</hi> England.</p>
            <p>The remainder of this Week was ſpent partly in ſettling Committees for General Grievances, and partly in ſet Speeches, Rhetorically declaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt, and diſſecting them.</p>
            <p>The remainder of the particular Tranſactions of this year of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England</hi> Aſſembled in Parliament, and of the year ſucceeding, 1641. I ſhall not here relate at large, but refer you to the Annals of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, written by this ingenious Author (from whom I have borrowed and tranſcribed the major part of my precedent Relations) who ends at the Death of the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> which was <hi>May</hi> the <hi>12th,</hi> 1641. And after that, I muſt refer you for the remainder of that year unto Sir <hi>Richard Baker</hi>'s Chronicle of the Kings of <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> But the particular heads of thoſe Tranſactions, as to matter of fact, I ſhall be willing here to recite for your (Courteous Readers) preſent ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in manner and form as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Several Petitions againſt Grievances.</item>
               <item>2. Priviledges of the Lords Houſe Vindicated.</item>
               <item>3. The Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland</hi> Impeached of high Treaſon.</item>
               <item>4. The <hi>Northern</hi> Armies in want.</item>
               <item>5. Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi> Enlarged.</item>
               <item>6. Juſtice <hi>Howard</hi> aſſaulted by a Papiſt.</item>
               <item>7. <hi>Prinn</hi> and <hi>Baſtwick</hi> enter <hi>London</hi> in Triumph.</item>
               <item>8. Secretary <hi>Windebanck</hi> flieth.</item>
               <item>9. Votes againſt Ship-money.</item>
               <item>10. The <hi>London</hi> Petition againſt Biſhops.</item>
               <item>11. The late Canons Damn'd.</item>
               <item>12. The Lord-Keeper <hi>Finch</hi> defends his Innocency.</item>
               <item>13. He is Voted Traitor upon four Conſiderations, and thereupon he flyeth beyond Sea.</item>
               <item>14. The Kings Speech for Biſhops.</item>
               <item>15. One <hi>Goodman</hi> a Prieſt reprieved.</item>
               <item>16. A Remonſtrance againſt <hi>Goodman</hi> the Prieſt.</item>
               <item>17. The Kings Anſwer to that Remonſtrance.</item>
               <item>18. The <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Commiſſioners Demands, and the Anſwer thereunto.</item>
               <item>19. A Match propounded between the Lady <hi>Mary</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>20. The Kings Speech to the Lords concerning that Match.</item>
               <item>21. Some Plots of the Papiſts.</item>
               <item>22. The Earl <hi>Berkly</hi> Impeacht of High-Treaſon.</item>
               <item>23. The King paſſeth a Bill for Trienial Parliaments, and his Speech concerning it.</item>
               <item>24. The Bill of Subſidies paſſeth at the ſame time, and Bonefires and other tokens of joy were made that night in the City of <hi>London,</hi> by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Parliament.</item>
               <item>25. <hi>William Laud,</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> accuſed of high Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in fourteen Artieles.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:59492:28"/>
26. The Lord <hi>Digbyes</hi> Speech for Epiſcopacy.</item>
               <item>27. The Charge againſt the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> is given, and his Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers thereunto, and <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> is appointed for his Trial.</item>
               <item>28. The Commons juſtifie their Charge by Law.</item>
               <item>29. The Earl anſwereth by Councel.</item>
               <item>30. The Commons Vote him guilty of High-treaſon.</item>
               <item>31. The Commons Petition the King againſt Papiſts, and the King's Anſwer.</item>
               <item>32. The Kings Speech to the Parliament in defence of the E of <hi>Strafford</hi>
               </item>
               <item>33. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> Marryeth the Lady <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>34. A Tumult in <hi>Westminſter</hi> crying for Juſtice againſt the Earl.</item>
               <item>35. A Proteſtation framed by the Commons.</item>
               <item>36. A Bill propounded for the continuation of the Parliament.</item>
               <item>37. The Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> Vored by the Lords Houſe guilty of High Treaſon.</item>
               <item>38. Two Bills tendered to the King, who is much perplext what An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to return.</item>
               <item>39. The Earl himſelf, by Letter deſires the King to paſs the Bill.</item>
               <item>40. Cenſures upon the Kings paſſing the Bill for the Parliaments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation.</item>
               <item>41. The Kings Letter in behalf of the Earl to the Houſe of Lords; and their anſwer thereunto.</item>
               <item>42. The Earl brought to the Scaffold, and his laſt Speech before his Execution.</item>
               <item>43. The Earls Character.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Here I muſt refer you at large to Sir</hi> Richard Baker, <hi>p.</hi> 511. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>44. The Earls Children reſtored to their Honour and Eſtates.</item>
               <item>45. The Earls of <hi>Hartford, Eſſex, Bedford, Warwick,</hi> Lord <hi>Say,</hi> with ſome others, made Privy-Councellors.</item>
               <item>46. The Lord Treaſurer and other great Officers reſign up their places.</item>
               <item>47. The Star-Chamber aboliſhed, and the high Commiſſion Court put down.</item>
               <item>48. Ship-money relinquiſh'd by the King.</item>
               <item>49. Five Judges for Ship-money Impeached of high Miſdemenours, and <hi>Berkly</hi> accuſed of high Treaſon.</item>
               <item>50. Several Laws paſſed by the King for regulating abuſes and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming Priviledges.</item>
               <item>51. The Treaty between the two Kingdoms confirmed.</item>
               <item>52. The Earl of <hi>Holland</hi> made General of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, and a Pole raiſed for the payment of them.</item>
               <item>53. Both Armies are Disbanded, and the King takes a Journey into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and there confers honours upon ſeveral perſons of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</item>
               <item>54. A Bloody Rebellion breaks forth in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>55. <hi>Owen O Conally,</hi> an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtant, diſcovers the Plot, prevents the ſeizure of <hi>Dublin Caeſtle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>56. The Earl of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> choſen Deputy of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>57. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion occaſioned by the inſurrection in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>58. The King receives Intelligence of what hapned in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59492:29"/>ſends Sir <hi>James Stuart</hi> with inſtructions thither, and moves the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Scotland</hi> for Aid, which they Excuſe.</item>
               <item>59. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> pretend the Kings Commiſſion for what they did, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to diſhearten the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and alſo feigned Letters that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would compell them to Proteſtancy.</item>
               <item>60. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebells poſſeſs themſelves of all ſtrong places in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>61. They contrary to Articles of Surrender, Maſſacre the poor <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> but ſave the <hi>Scots.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>62. The Parliament of <hi>England</hi> deſigns Money for <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>63. Forces raiſed to go againſt the Rebells.</item>
               <item>64. The Earl of <hi>Ormond</hi> made Lieutenant-General of the Forces there.</item>
               <item>65. A Regiment ſent to <hi>Ireland</hi> under Sir <hi>Simon Hartcourt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>66. The King returns out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Parliament preſent a Remonſtrance to him at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> as alſo a Petition with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance.</item>
               <item>67. An Act publiſhed in <hi>Scotland</hi> againſt Levying Arms without the Kings Commiſſion.</item>
               <item>68. The King receives the Parliaments Petition, but deſires them not to publiſh the Remonſtrance.</item>
               <item>69 The Remonſtrance is Ordered to be publiſhed in all parts of the Kingdom, and the King anſwers the Petition, and Vindicates himſelf from the Aſperſions of the Remonſtrance.</item>
               <item>70. The Commons paſs a Bill for diſabling all in Holy Orders to exerciſe temporal Juriſdiction.</item>
               <item>71. The tumult upon the Lords ſlighting the Bill, comes to their Houſe, and clamour againg the Biſhops, and ſome of the Commons ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie thoſe tumults.</item>
               <item>72. The Lords ſends a Writ directed to the Sheriffs and Juſtices to ſuppreſs thoſe tumults.</item>
               <item>73. Whereupon the Conſtables and Juſtices are ſent for by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</item>
               <item>74. The Biſhops Proteſtations againſt the actions of the Parliament, and they are charged with high Treaſon, and committed to the <hi>Tower,</hi> where they continued about four Months.</item>
               <item>75. The Parliament Petition the King for a Guard.</item>
               <item>76. The King denies the Petition, and chargeth <hi>Kimbolton</hi> and five Members more of the Commons with high Treaſon.</item>
               <item>77. The Commons juſtifie the accuſed Members.</item>
               <item>78. The King comes to the Houſe to demand the Delivery of the five Members, and the Commons Vote this a breach of Priviledge.</item>
               <item>79. The King removes to <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> and ſends a Meſſage to the Parliament.</item>
               <item>80. The Commons Petition the King for the Militia to be put into their hands.</item>
               <item>81. The Queen accompanies the Princeſs <hi>Mary</hi> into <hi>Holland,</hi> and the King removes to <hi>York,</hi> and there iſſues out Commiſſions of Array. And ſo, <hi>Finis Coronat Opus,</hi> I have proceeded to the laſt day of 1641. For I find <hi>March</hi> 28. 1642. The King and Parliament differ about who ſhall be chief Commander at Sea; where I am willing to leave them, and dare not launch out any farther, as to the Merits of the Cauſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:59492:29"/>
And now in the cloſe of all, if you will pleaſe to give me leave faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to examine and compare together the Tranſactions, Principles, and Practices of the Commons of <hi>England</hi> (in particular, as being Aſſembled in Parliament) <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1640, and 1641, as alſo <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1680, and 1681. (whoſe Tranſactions, Debates, and Speeches, are all ſo lately Printed, that I need not here inſert the Particulars, but refer you unto the Debates themſelves) And I do clearly find the ſame Engliſh Spirit, ſo far as 1641. (pray take notice I proceed no further in this <hi>Multum in Parvo</hi>) runs almoſt exactly Parallel with the preſent years of 80, and 81. And when you have peruſed and ſeriouſly conſidered them within your ſelves, I do preſume (and am very apt to conjecture) that you who are of a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber mind, and wiſh from your Heart and Soul all Peace, Proſperity, and Happineſs to your King and Country, That you will ſay with me, That although they are not enough to ſatisfie and ſilence an high Tory and bloody Papiſt, yet they are Arguments and Demonſtrations ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in Conſeience to convince any Atheiſt in his ſober mind, of the Reality and good Intentions (againſt Popery and Slavery, many times ſlily introduced by ſome unworthy Sycophants, and corrupt Miniſters of State) of the before-mentioned precedent Parliaments.</p>
            <p>And although we live at preſent in an Age of Wonders, <hi>viz.</hi> of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Signs, wonderful and moſt prodigious Comets and Blazing Stars, and wonderful Apparitions (for a particular whereof, <hi>viz.</hi> of ſuch as have happened in the laſt year 1680 pray read Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Neſs</hi> his late Book, the Title whereof is, <hi>Wonderful Signs for Wonderful Times</hi>) yet I ſay the major part of us do turn all theſe things into perfect Ridicule and Scorn, and are far from deterring us from the evil of our ways, but do ſtill run on, (<hi>Jehu</hi>-like) and perſiſt in our accuſtomed Sins, and <hi>Dalilah</hi>-like Provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt God, and are all of us (the Lord of Heaven knows) in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unprepared frame, temper, and diſpoſition, to meet him (and to kiſs the Rod) in the ways of his Judgments, when they ſhall come ſuddenly upon us, like an armed Man, and there ſhall be none to deliver us out of his avenging hand. <hi>Him that hath an Ear to hear, let him hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And among the many Wonders which we have already had, I have made bold here to inſert one more, which for ought I know may ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly come to paſs in the midſt of us, (and pray pardon my plainneſs and well-meaning, and hearty wiſhes therein) the which you may pleaſe to peruſe, in manner and form as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>A Wonder ſtrange I will you tell,</l>
               <l>From Heaven 'twill be, and not from Hill,</l>
               <l>When as King <hi>CHARLES</hi> ſhall be content,</l>
               <l>In Love to meet his Parliament,</l>
               <l>And let them ſit, For to Redreſs</l>
               <l>All Grievances, both more or leſs,</l>
               <l>Which in our Church and State have been,</l>
               <l>E'er ſince our Bleſſed Virgin Queen</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil this day, Which make us bleed,</l>
               <l>And cry, We want ſome nurſing ſeed,</l>
               <l>To Cool us in our Scarlet Feaver;</l>
               <l>This is the time, or elſe for ever</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:59492:30"/>
Adieu to Peace. War will begin</l>
               <l>In this our Land. The man of Sin</l>
               <l>Begins to Rant. And to declare</l>
               <l>Againſt us all, He will make War,</l>
               <l>Who will not ſtoop unto his Power,</l>
               <l>The Sword or <hi>Smithfield</hi> ſhall devoure</l>
               <l>Such Northern Bastards which have done</l>
               <l>Such Miſchief to his Triple Crown.</l>
               <l>But when our Prince, King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Great</l>
               <l>Shall Diſſipate this Southern Heat,</l>
               <l>And when our Truſtees ſhall declare,</l>
               <l>A War againſt Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Chair,</l>
               <l>(And him that doth Poſſeſs the ſame,</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf at last ſhall blame)</l>
               <l>And ſo ſecure us from thoſe Brats</l>
               <l>Which to the Church and State are Rats,</l>
               <l>And ſtill do Plot to keep us under,</l>
               <l>And Gnaw our Church and State in ſunder;</l>
               <l>Oh! then Sweet Peace ſhall Enter in:</l>
               <l>And after that, the Man of Sin</l>
               <l>Shall ſoon be Routed, out, from hence</l>
               <l>By the Powerful Charms and Influence</l>
               <l>Of Prince and People, Joyn'd in one,</l>
               <l>Like to the Father and the Son;</l>
               <l>Till then, and not till then, will here inſue</l>
               <l>A Lasting Peace; till then, Reader, Adieu:</l>
               <l>And know till then that I am well content</l>
               <l>To ſuffer for an Honeſt Parliament,</l>
               <l>So long as they ſhall prove ſo Loyal,</l>
               <l>As we of late, have had the Tryal</l>
               <l>Although miſcalled all Bugbears</l>
               <l>By ſome proud Raſcals, whoſe ſoft Ears</l>
               <l>May yet in time perchance to feel</l>
               <l>The Dint of their Provoked Steel,</l>
               <l>And make them ſtop their mouths for fear</l>
               <l>A Triple Tree ſhould them beſmear,</l>
               <l>Who have ſo boldly here of late</l>
               <l>Belcht out against our Triple State</l>
               <l>Such Spite and Venome, in one hour</l>
               <l>Enough (ſay ſome) for to devour,</l>
               <l>Our Triple League within our Land,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second doth Command,</l>
               <l>By Laws Eſtabliſht with Conſent</l>
               <l>Of three Eſtates in Parliament</l>
               <l>King Lords and Commons, Oh this State</l>
               <l>Cannot be Cruſht without a broken Pate</l>
               <l>Given to ſome, who still do Lurke.</l>
               <l>Within our Bowels, who much like the Kirk</l>
               <l>In other Countries, and would ſtraightway bring</l>
               <l>All to their Bow, and likewiſe every thing</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:59492:30"/>
Which Thwarts their Humors, And whoſe fair pretence</l>
               <l>Is ſtill their Zeal unto Omnipotence,</l>
               <l>Although in this (Heaven knows) they are all evil</l>
               <l>And Pope and they may ſhake hands with the —</l>
               <l>As all infallible in their own proud ſence:</l>
               <l>God keep us from their power and Influence</l>
               <l>Within our Land, and let all Christians ſay</l>
               <l>To this Amen. And here wee'l part the Fray!</l>
               <l>Although continue Praying Till we ſee</l>
               <l>This <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity made viſible in Three</l>
            </q>
            <p>And that you may ſee as unlikly a Wonder and Prediction may come to paſs, I will relate unto you who have not already ſeen or heard of it, a ſtrange and moſt wonderful Prediction, the moſt part whereof is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready come to paſs, (and that within our Times and Remembrance) the which ſaid moſt wonderful Prediction is of many hundred years ſtanding, the which I did formerly take out of a Book, the Title whereof is <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains Genius,</hi> Printed here in <hi>London</hi> about 1646. or 1647. long before His Majeſties moſt wonderful Reſtoration, and ſome ſpace of time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore His late Majeſties moſt inauſpicious and moſt aſtoniſhing Decola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The contents of the ſaid moſt wonderful and antient Prophecy out of the ſaid Book, you may pleaſe to peruſe as followeth., <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>WHen here a <hi>Scot</hi> ſhall think his Throne to ſet</l>
               <l>Above the Circle of a <hi>Britiſh</hi> King,</l>
               <l>He ſhall a dateleſs Parliament beget,</l>
               <l>From whence a furicus Armed brood ſhall ſpring;</l>
               <l>That Army ſhall beget a wild Confuſion,</l>
               <l>Confuſion ſhall an Anarthy beget,</l>
               <l>That Anarchy ſhall bring forth in Concluſion</l>
               <l>A Creature which you have no name for yet;</l>
               <l>That Creature ſhall Conceive a Sickly State,</l>
               <l>Which ſhall an Ariſtocracy produce;</l>
               <l>The many-headed Beaſt not liking that</l>
               <l>To raiſe Demoeracy ſhall rather chuſe;</l>
               <l>And then Democracies Production ſhall</l>
               <l>A Moon Calfe be, which ſome a Mole do call;</l>
               <l>So acting for a while, few men ſhall know</l>
               <l>Whether among them there be a Supream or no.</l>
               <l>Five of them, ſhall ſubdue the other five,</l>
               <l>And then thoſe five ſhall by a doubtful ſtrife</l>
               <l>Each others Death, ſo happily Contrive,</l>
               <l>That they ſhall Die, to live a better life</l>
               <l>And out of their corruption riſe there ſhall</l>
               <l>A true Supream, Acknowledged by ail,<note place="margin">His Majeſties Reſtanration plainly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told.</note>
               </l>
               <l>In which the power of all the Five ſhall be</l>
               <l>With <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity made viſible in Three,</l>
               <l>King, People, Parliaments, with Prieſts and Peers,</l>
               <l>Shall be a while your Emulous Grandees,</l>
               <l>Make a Confuſed Pentarchy ſome years,</l>
               <l>And leave off their diſtinct Claims by degrees;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:59492:31"/>
And then ſhall Righteouſneſs aſcend the Throne,</l>
               <l>Then Love, and Truth, and Peace, Re-enter ſhall;</l>
               <l>Then Faith and Reaſon ſhall agree in One,</l>
               <l>And all the Virtues to their Councel Call.</l>
               <l>Then timely after this, there ſhall ariſe</l>
               <l>That Kingdom and That happy Government,</l>
               <l>Which is the Scope of all thoſe Prophecies</l>
               <l>That further Truths obſcurely Repreſent.</l>
               <l>But how this ſhall be done, few men ſhall ſee;</l>
               <l>For wrought in Clouds and Darkneſs it ſhall be:</l>
               <l>And ere it comes to paſs in Publick View,</l>
               <l>Moſt of theſe following Signs ſhall firſt Enſue:</l>
               <l>A King ſhall willingly, himſelf <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nking,</l>
               <l>And thereby grow far greater than before;</l>
               <l>The Prieſts their Prieſthood to Contempt ſhall bring,</l>
               <l>And Piety ſhall thereby thrive the more:</l>
               <l>A Parliament it ſelf ſhall overthrow,</l>
               <l>And thereby ſhall a better being gain;</l>
               <l>The Peers by ſetting of themſelves below,</l>
               <l>A more Enobling Honour ſhall obtain:</l>
               <l>The People for a while, ſhall be Enſlaved,</l>
               <l>And that ſhall make them for the future free;</l>
               <l>By Private Loſs the Publick ſhall be ſaved;</l>
               <l>An Army ſhall by yeilding, Victor be.</l>
               <l>Then ſhall God own his People and their Cauſe,</l>
               <l>The Laws Corruption ſhall Reform ths Laws.</l>
               <l>And Bullocks of the Largest Northern breed</l>
               <l>Shall fatted be, where now ſcarce Sheep can feed.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And here although I cannot Divine, heither dare I aſſume to my ſelf ſo much boldneſs as to preſcribe the way and means, in order to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of this moſt ſtrange and wonderful Recited Prophecy, yet I am apt to Conjecture, and do perſwade my ſelf (if ever it ſhall come to paſs) That it will be in a very Critical time of Common and Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Danger (peradventure the Dread of a Popiſh Succeſſor, and the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Conſequence thereof) when ſome good Prince or other ſhall be ſo far graciouſly pleaſed to condeſcend to his grand <hi>Council,</hi> as to make three Kingdoms by his Royal <hi>Fiat, (aut Le Roy Le Veult)</hi> for the future Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive, and ſo they may ſtill introduce the Royal Blood and Legitimate Line <hi>ad Infinitum,</hi> that are truly Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>And now Courage (moſt Noble Loyal and Curteous Readers) what ſay you if his preſent Majeſty of Great <hi>Brittain</hi> ſhould be this Perſon of Quality here intimated and deſcribed in this moſt wonderful and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Prophecy (a Prediction I muſt needs Confeſs moſt proper for ſuch wonderful times as we now live in) would you not all unanimouſly and with loud Acclamations throw up your Caps and Beavers into the Air, and cry, <hi>Vive le Roy,</hi> (or, <hi>Currat Lex &amp; vivat Rex?)</hi> And if ſo, for my own part I ſhould yet hope to ſee (if it ſhall pleaſe my Gracious God to lend me a little longer time of health and ſtrength) many Halcyon and moſt happy days in the Land and Nation of my Nativity before I go away
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59492:31"/>hence and ſhall be ſeen no more. And that an happy union and good cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence between his preſent Majeſty and his future Parliaments, without the leaſt ſuſpition or jealouſie one of another, may yet come to paſs in our days, I do moſt humbly beſeech thy Divine Majeſty, who are the Lord God Almighty, to grant for thy great names ſake, and for thy Vicegerents ſake, and for his Peoples ſake (who are truly Loyal and obedient Subjects) in and through thy moſt dear and well beloved Son the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in whom thou art well pleaſed, and whom (by thy free grace, goodneſs and moſt ſtupendious mercy and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to thy poor creatures) is the Lord and giver of everlaſting Life, to all thoſe who ſhall moſt faithfully, and moſt ſincerely, though but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectly obey him. And now to him with thy eternal Majeſty; who art King Immortal, Inviſible, and only wiſe God, by the aſſiſtance of thy holy (and for ever bleſſed) Spirit of Grace, I do moſt humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to render, give, and aſcribe all honour, glory, laud and praiſe, might, Majeſty, reverential fear, and all humble adoration, from this time forth and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now in the cloſe of all, Whereas in my Title-Page I have there intimated how <hi>Magna Charta</hi> was moſt ſolemnly and moſt wonderfully (even to the aſtoniſhment of the Spectators) ratified, pronounced and proclaimed, and therefore muſt not now leave you in the dark, as to that particular; but refer you to the <hi>Packet of Advice from Rome,</hi> Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 50. (the which, in my ſlender apprehenſion, deſerves to be written in Letters of Gold upon the Walls of both Houſes of Parliament) And for your preſent (and I hope pleaſant) ſatisfaction I have here inferted and preſented you with the ſame at large.</p>
            <p>HAving preſented the Reader with the moſt remarkable Tranſactions of <hi>Papal</hi> Tyranny in Foreign Parts down to the year 1254, 'tis time to look homewards, and obſerve <hi>Eccleſiaſtic</hi> Occurrences in <hi>England;</hi> our laſt Diſcourſe of that kind terminating with the death of King <hi>John,</hi> to whom ſucceeded his Son <hi>Henry,</hi> the third of that name; for though by reaſon of the <hi>Fewds</hi> between <hi>John</hi> and his <hi>Barons,</hi> they had invited over <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King's Son, and many had to him ſworn Allegiance; yet the Father being dead; and his faults buried with him; they did not think fit to yield up themſelves to the <hi>French</hi> Man's Yoak, who already began to exerciſe an inſufferable <hi>Tyranny</hi> wherever he had Power: And although the Pope had at firſt <hi>encourag'd</hi> the Barons in their Rebellion, yet when once he had <hi>hector'd</hi> King <hi>John</hi> into a Reſignation of his Crown, he became his <hi>Patron,</hi> and forbad <hi>Lewis</hi> from intermedling with the Kingdom, as being then (forſooth!) <hi>part of S.</hi> Peter's <hi>Patrimony,</hi> and therefore <hi>excommunicated Lewis</hi> for the Invaſion, which engag'd moſt of the Clergy to oppoſe him: And ſo <hi>Henry</hi> on the <hi>28th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1216. was Crown'd, being then in the <hi>10th</hi> year of his Age; and <hi>Lewis</hi> being routed at <hi>Lincoln,</hi> was glad to come to a Treaty, quit his Pretenſions, and moſt diſhonourably retreat into <hi>France.</hi> Yet 'tis obſervable, that the Clergy were then ſuch faſt Friends to their Head the <hi>Pope,</hi> and ſo little regardful of the <hi>Deſcent in the Right Line,</hi> that they would not accept <hi>Henry</hi> for their King, without making him firſt do <hi>Homage</hi> to the Holy Chureh of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> for his Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59492:32"/>
               <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſwearing to pay the 1000 Marks <hi>per Annum</hi> which his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had promiſed to that <hi>See. (Matth. Paris, fol.</hi> 278.)</p>
            <p>And beſides, to bring <hi>Griſts</hi> to the <hi>Roman</hi> Mill, the Pope's Legate at that time in <hi>England,</hi> immediately on the Departure of Prince <hi>Lewis,</hi> ſent his <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> all over the Realm, and whomſoever they would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover to have ſided with him, <hi>Conſenſuetiam Leviſſimo, Though in the leaſt degree,</hi> muſt atone the Crime with a large Sum; inſomuch as the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi> before he could be reſtored to his Biſhoprick, was forc'd to pay 1000 <hi>Marks</hi> to the Pope's uſe, and 1000 to the Legate, (for the <hi>little Rogue</hi> would have <hi>ſuips</hi> in the prey with the great <hi>One</hi>) and many other Biſhops, and Religious Men, were glad to empty their Pockets to him at the ſame rate. <hi>Matth. Paris, fol.</hi> 218.</p>
            <p>In the year 1220. the Pope was pleaſed to make <hi>Hugh,</hi> formerly Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Lineoln,</hi> a <hi>Saint;</hi> and ſince the manner of his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-Holineſs</hi>'s de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the ſame may be Divertive to the common <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reader, I ſhall give you the very words of his Letter (Tranſlated) as I find it in <hi>Matth. Paris, fol.</hi> 298. <q>
                  <hi>Honorius,</hi> Servant of the Servants of God, to all out well-beloved Sons; the Faithful of Chriſt, that ſhall inſpect theſe Preſents, Greeting and Apoſtolick Benediction: The worthineſs of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Piety does make famous his Holy Ones and Elect, placed in the Bliſs of the Celeſtial Kingdom, by the ſhining forth of their Miracles ſtill upon Earth, that the Devotion of the Faithful being thereby ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up, may with due Veneration implore their Aid and Suffrages; ſince therefore we are fully ſatisfied, that the Bounty of Heaven hath illuſtrated <hi>Hugh</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> as well in his Life, as after his Death, with a multitude of Famous Miracles: We have thought fit to Enroll him in the Catalogue of Saints, and admoniſh and exhort you all in the Lord, That you devoutly implore his Patronage and Interceſſion for you with Almighty God; farther Commanding, That the day of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe be henceforwards every year devoutly Celebrated as a <hi>Holyday.</hi> Dated at <hi>Viterbium</hi> the <hi>13th</hi> Calend of <hi>March,</hi> in the fourth year of our Popedom.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But how much a Saint ſoever he was, we meet with another Biſhop as very a Devil; for about this time a Quarrel happening between <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> and the <hi>Monks</hi> of the ſame Church; they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of him to the Pope, who ſeem'd much concern'd at his many hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Crimes, and preſently ſent over a Letter in theſe Terms—<q>
                  <hi>Honori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> Biſhop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the Biſhops of <hi>Salisbury, Ely,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Greeting and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Benediction:</hi> It is fit for us to be ſo be ſo delighted in the ſweet Savour of a good opinion of our Brethren and Fellow-Labourers, as not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nive at Vices in thoſe that are Peſtilent, ſince it becomes not us for the Reverence of the Order to bear with Sinners, whoſe Guilt renders them as worthy of as many Deaths, as they tranſmit Examples of Perdition to thoſe that are under them, who are too apt to <hi>imitate</hi> only the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravaties</hi> of their Superiours. Hence it is, that ſince things too far diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant from Epiſcopal Honeſty, have very often been ſuggeſted unto us concerning our Venerable Brother the Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with ſuch repeated Complaints, we cannot ſuffer the ſaid Biſhop to continue in his Enormities to the Deſtruction of many, for we are inform'd, That ſince he was advanced to the Office of a Biſhop, he
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59492:32"/>has been guilty of <hi>Blood,</hi> and <hi>Simony</hi> and <hi>Adultery,</hi> and <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> and <hi>Rapine,</hi> and <hi>Perjury, [A pretty parcel of Vertues for a Biſhop, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what different from thoſe</hi> 1 Tim. 3.] That he hath oppreſs'd Clerks and Orphans, obſtructed the Teſtaments of the deceaſed; that he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves not the Statutes of the General Council, nor ever prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the Word of God to the People, <hi>['Tis a wonder that ſmall fault was mentioned]</hi> hath often ſworn before many, that the Church of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> ſhall never have Peace as long as he lives: That a Monk com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining to him, that his Servants had drawn him out of a Church, and beat him till the Blood came: He anſwered, It had been well, if they had beat out his Brains, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We therefore, that we may not be guilty of the faults of others, if we ſhould <hi>wink</hi> at ſuch Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſince the Clamour thereof has aſcended, ſo that we can diſſemble it no longer; think it agreeable to our Office to go down and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe things be ſo or no: Therefore by theſe our <hi>Apoſtolical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,</hi> we Command you our Brethren to examine and enquire into the premiſes, and report the ſame to us under Seal, that we may Decree therein as God ſhall order. Dated at <hi>Viterb.</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee the Pope can Cant, and pretend great Zeal to correct the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, but pray obſerve the end on't; Theſe Biſhops being met to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the Buſineſs, the Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> preſently Appeals to the Pope in Perſon, and then they could proceed no farther, but away both he and the Monks his Adverſaries muſt trudge to <hi>Rome,</hi> whither he private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſent beforehand two of his Clerks with a <hi>good Sum of Money,</hi> which ſo ſweeten'd the Pope, that he receiv'd him very kindly: <hi>Et poſt multas coram Papa Altercationes, Immoderatis profuſis Expenſis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And after many Wranglings before the Pope, and vaſt Expences, both Biſhop and Monks were ſent back</hi> (as wiſe and honeſt as they were) <hi>to agree together as well as they could.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which was moſt memorable in this Kings Reign was an <hi>Act,</hi> which tho' reſpecting the <hi>temporal Good</hi> of the Kingdom, yet it being Tranſacted chiefly by the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and with <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Ceremonies,</hi> it may not be improper to inſert it into this Work.</p>
            <p>The Reader muſt note, That when K. <hi>Hen.</hi> III. was become 16 years old, the Pope took upon himſelf, for a ſmall Spill, privately ſent him by ſome corrupt Courtiers, to declare him of Age to Govern himſelf, and therefore all Caſtles were to be render'd up into the Kings hands. This prov'd the Rock of Offence, whilſt ſome obey'd the Pope, and oppos'd thoſe as <hi>Rebels</hi> that put more confidence in their Caſtles, than in the Kings good nature, or rather in that of his upſtart Counſellors. Hence firſt ſprang a Civil Broyl, thence want of Money, then a Parliament, wherein the Grand Charter of <hi>England</hi>'s Liberties once more was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed for a Sum of <hi>Money:</hi> For only upon condition of renewing the ſame, would the Eſtates allow <hi>Supplies;</hi> many <hi>Promiſes</hi> the King makes, and after that, <hi>Oaths;</hi> yet no performance, but pretends <hi>Wars</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and againſt <hi>Infidels.</hi> But ſtill his <hi>people</hi> finding them all but <hi>preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and ill ſucceſs to attend all his Enterprizes, refuſe to ſupply him for the <hi>Holy War:</hi> Then he ſeems <hi>penitent,</hi> and pours out new <hi>promiſes</hi> to obſerve <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and Seals it with the moſt <hi>ſolemn Execration</hi> that is to be found in the Womb of Story, and ſo punctually Recorded, as if God would
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59492:33"/>have <hi>all Generations</hi> to remember it as the Seal of the <hi>Covenant</hi> between the King of <hi>England</hi> and his people: It was done in Parliament, where the Lords Temporal and Spiritual, Clergy men, Knights, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with <hi>Tapers</hi> in their hands burning, the King himſelf alſo ſtanding with a chearful Countenance, holding his open hand upon his Breaſt; the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> pronounc'd this Curſe, as it is <hi>verbatim</hi> Recorded by <hi>Matth. Paris, fol.</hi> 839.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the</hi> Authority <hi>of God Omnipotent, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, and of the Glorious</hi> Mother <hi>of God the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and of the bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Paul, <hi>and of all other Apoſtles, and of the</hi> Holy Martyr <hi>and Archbiſhop</hi> Thomas, <hi>and of all the</hi> Martyrs, <hi>and of the Bleſſed</hi> Edward <hi>King of</hi> England, <hi>and of all</hi> Confeſſors <hi>and Virgins, and of all the Saints of God: We</hi> Excommunicate, <hi>and Anathematize, and Sequeſter from our our Holy Mother the Church, all thoſe which henceforth knowingly and Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſhall deprive or ſpoil the</hi> Church <hi>of her</hi> Right; <hi>and all thoſe that ſhall by any</hi> Art <hi>or</hi> Wit <hi>raſhly violate diminiſh, or change ſecretly or openly in Deed, Word, or Council, by croſſing in part or in</hi> whole, <hi>thoſe Eccleſiaſtical Liberties, or ancient approved Cuſtoms of the Kingdom, eſpecially the</hi> Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>and free Cuſtoms which are contained in the</hi> Charters <hi>of the Common Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of</hi> England, <hi>and the Forreſts, granted by our Lord the King to the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Prelates, Earls, Barons, Knights, and</hi> Freeholders. <hi>And all thoſe who have publiſhed, or being publiſhed have obſerved any Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, Ordinances, or thing againſt them, or any thing therein contained, or which have brought in any</hi> Cuſtoms <hi>to the contrary, or obſerved them being brought in, and all Writers of ſuch Ordinances, or Councils, or Executioners, and all ſuch as ſhall preſume to</hi> judge <hi>according to ſuch Ordinances: All and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch perſons as are, or at any time ſhall be, knowingly guilty of any ſuch matters, ſhall</hi> ipſo facto <hi>incur this Sentence; and ſuch as are</hi> ignorantly <hi>guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhall incur the ſame, if being admoniſh'd, they within</hi> 15 <hi>days after amend not. For everlaſting Memory whereof, we hereunto put our Seals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far the words of the Curſe, nor was the manner of pronouncing it leſs dreadful; for immediately as ſoon as the Charters and this Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence was read and ſign'd, they then all throwing down their Tapers <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh'd</hi> and <hi>ſmoaking,</hi> ſaid, <hi>So let all that go againſt this Curſe be extinct and stink in Hell:</hi> And the King having all the while continued in the poſture before mentioned, ſaid, <hi>So God me help, I will obſerve all thoſe things ſincerely and faithfully, as I am a man, as I am a Chriſtian, as I am a Knight, and as I am a King Crowned and Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pare but away ſome few Superſtitions, and ſearch the <hi>Hiſtory of all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> you will not find a <hi>parallel</hi> hereunto, ſo ſeriouſly <hi>compos'd,</hi> ſo ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>pronounc'd</hi> with an <hi>Amen</hi> from the Repreſentative Body of the whole Kingdom, put in <hi>Writing,</hi> under <hi>Seal, preſerv'd</hi> to Poſterity, and (give me leave to add) <hi>vindicated</hi> by God himſelf in the Ruine of ſo many Oppoſers; for never has any <hi>Prince, Favourite, Councellor,</hi> or <hi>corrupt Judge,</hi> from that time to this, endeavour'd to act contrary to the Eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of the ſaid <hi>great Charter,</hi> but firſt or laſt it has <hi>cruſh'd</hi> them into Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, or great Calamity. Yet how little this King <hi>Henry</hi> regarded it, I ſhall acquaint you in the very words of the Hiſtorian—<hi>Soluto Concilio Rex Confeſtim peſſimo uſus Concilio omnia praedicta Cogitabat Infirmare,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Grand Council</hi> (or Parliament) <hi>was no ſooner broke up, but the King fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59492:33"/>lewd and pernicious Council, contriv'd how to weaken and undo it; for 'twas told him, That he would not be King, or at least not Lord and Maſter of</hi> England, <hi>if all thoſe Liberties ſhould be obſerv'd, as</hi> John <hi>his Father had experienc'd, who rather choſe to dye, than thus to be ſhackled and trampled on by his Subjects:</hi> And theſe Whiſperers of the Devil (<hi>Suſurrones Satanae,</hi> ſo honeſt <hi>Matth.</hi> calls them) added— <hi>You need not value it if you do break your Vows, and incur this Curſe, for the Pope for an hundred or two of Pounds will Abſolve you. 'Tis well enough, that by ſigning the Confirmation of theſe Characters you have got a</hi> Tenth, <hi>which will amount to many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Marks; and if you will but give the Pope a little portion of it, he will Abſolve you, even though the Curſe be ratified by himſelf, for he that has Power to Bind can Looſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus by the villany of <hi>ill Ministers,</hi> and the <hi>knavery</hi> of the Pope, this Prince was led into <hi>Deceit, Perjury, Injustice,</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> to his own <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Trouble,</hi> and the unſpeakable <hi>Damage</hi> of the Realm.</p>
            <p>And if this honeſt and well intended Narrative, either in the whole or in part, ſhall be deemed neceſſary and convenient at this juncture of time, for the preſent and future ſatisfaction either of Prince or People, or ſhall contribute any thing towards a firm and ſolid Foundation and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment upon the true Baſis of Univerſal Love, Charity, and good will, among the many conteſting Parties at this day in the midſt of us, (for <hi>ſine procul dubio</hi> we ſhall never be happy till that time be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) I have my deſire. The height of whoſe real ambition is, to render my ſelf worthy of my Soveraign Lord the King and my Countries acception. And having now ventured to expoſe it unto publick view, I have <hi>in Cognito</hi> (by my honeſt and truſty poſt Pidgeon) conveighed it into the hands of a Loyal Subject and good Citizen, as I am informed, (and if my Information be not true, pray let me not therefore be Libeld) called by the name of honeſt <hi>Dick Janeway,</hi> for the Publication thereof.</p>
            <p>And what though he be buffeted and baited,<note place="margin">For I muſt confeſs I have not peruſed it.</note> in every pittiful week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (I had almoſt ſaid <hi>Quotidian</hi>) Pamphlet, like an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſa Major &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſa Minor,</hi> (This being the Title of a Book newly Printed, and newly come forth, which I preſume doth face in oppoſition to mine, and peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it may ſerve by the way of <hi>Post Ponae,</hi> as a Reſponce thereunto) by a company of high-flown ſcurrilous <hi>Tories, Tantivies,</hi> and <hi>Towzers,</hi> who only bark where they cannot bite; yet I ſay, I do not look upon honeſt <hi>Dick,</hi> to be a worſe Subject, a worſe Citizen, or a worſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths-man, for all that; for I do perſwade my ſelf (having ſome ſmall and little acquaintance with them, although I could wiſh <hi>toto cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> I had leſs) their moſt venemous and malicious tongues are no ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>(toto in toto et in quilibet parte)</hi> and bleſſed be God; that we do yet live (but how long the Lord of Heaven onely knows if theſe men ſhould rule the roaſt,) under ſo mild limited and well tempered Government. Wherein as honeſt man and a Loyal Subject may be Protected, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended from the furious and bold Attempts of theſe blood thirſty Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſinates, who make it their buſineſs <hi>(journelament ſe vous aſſeure)</hi> not onely to Libell the preſent and beſt eſtabliſhed Legiſlative Government this day under the Sun, (<hi>viz.</hi> by King Lords and Commons) but alſo if by any probable or poſſible means they can, by their continual charging the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59492:34"/>moſt Loyal Subjects of His Preſent Majeſty with Republican plots, and ſham-plots, (Although by the overuling and good Providence of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, conſtantly found out and betrayed) on purpoſe to render them moſt odious to the Government and to bring us all at laſt (if they can) into a moſt miſerable ſtate of horror and confuſion, and from ſuch Loyal Subjects, <hi>Tantivy</hi> Abhorrours, and moſt Prophane and Diſſolute Debauchee;, Iſay, <hi>iterum atque iterum. Libera nos Domine.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>
               <hi>The</hi> CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
            <head>TO that moſt high and lofty proud Prelate (if theſe lines ſhould ever fall into His Unholy hands) the Fallible and Infallible Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> in particular, and to all the reſt of his Fanatical, Atheſtical, and Papiſtical adjuncts and adherents whatſoever.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>GIve ear, proud Rebels; Blood-ſuckers draw near;</l>
               <l>Add to this doleful Piece your briniſh Tear;</l>
               <l>To ſee a Nation poyſoned in their Blood,</l>
               <l>With Pride and Faction, not well underſtood</l>
               <l>By our Great <hi>CHARLES:</hi> Oh <hi>Rome,</hi> 'tis ſuch as you</l>
               <l>Would cruſh our Captain, and his Kingdoms too,</l>
               <l>By your accurst Caballs; which to prevent,</l>
               <l>God ſend our King and his next Parliament,</l>
               <l>So fully to agree, that ſo at length they may</l>
               <l>Condemn you all, as Ravenous Beaſts of pray,</l>
               <l>Who worry would, our Sheep and Shephered too,</l>
               <l>If not prevented, by a moſt Noble Crew.</l>
               <l>Of Loyal Subjects, that will faithful be</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Death, for Engliſh Monarchy.</l>
               <l>Which is ſo bounded by the Supream Law</l>
               <l>Of God and nature, which will over Awe</l>
               <l>Your Plots and Shamplots and your Truſty Friend</l>
               <l>Who fain would bring our Captain to his end:</l>
               <l>But Heavens forbid ſo baſe an Act as this,</l>
               <l>Should e'er take place within this Realm of Bliſs,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>England</hi> I mean, an Earthly Paradice,</l>
               <l>Before infected by ſuch bold Dormice,</l>
               <l>And Sons of Scarlet Whore, the which are all</l>
               <l>Sworn Enemies to the State, and to <hi>Whitehall:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs you get a King, who ſtraight muſt pay</l>
               <l>Homage to you, and by your Scepter ſway</l>
               <l>His future Legal rights, and he muſt Dance</l>
               <l>After your Pipe, like <hi>Italy, Spain,</hi> and <hi>France:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And many places more when you ſhall ſend</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Servus Servorum</hi> to your Truſty Friend;</l>
               <l>Who muſt your Benediction ſoon obſerve,</l>
               <l>Or elſe Incur diſpleaſure, to deſerve</l>
               <l>Your Thundring Bull of Excommunication when</l>
               <l>But once Pronounc'd, ſtraightway Allegiance then</l>
               <l>Muſt vaile their Top Sails, to your Bloody Flagg</l>
               <l>Or elſe by'th Maſs you'l catch them by the Crag</l>
               <l>And hang them up, as Traitors to your State,</l>
               <l>Since you have ſworn to admit of no ſuch Mate.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:59492:34"/>
By holy Croſs and by Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Chair</l>
               <l>(Whoſe Vicar general under Chriſt you are</l>
               <l>If lies be true) who being his Succeſſor</l>
               <l>In faith and vertue, <hi>Montebanck</hi> not <hi>Peter</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You are, who ner'e could dream of ſuch a doting Fool</l>
               <l>Should er'e ſucceed upon his ſacred stool</l>
               <l>(To feed Chriſts Lambs, but hark, inſtead of that</l>
               <l>You fill your Coffers, with their Blood and fat)</l>
               <l>When as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid, upon this Rock I'le build</l>
               <l>My Holy Church, look Pope have you fulfil'd</l>
               <l>His Sacred Word, which was not on that Bone,</l>
               <l>(You have ſo oft built up your tottering Throne)</l>
               <l>Of <hi>ſuper hunc Petrum,</hi> You are a Lyar,</l>
               <l>'Twas <hi>ſuper hanc Petram,</hi> I'le build my Quire.</l>
               <l>Of thy confeſſion <hi>Peter,</hi> o're which the Gates of Hell</l>
               <l>Shall ne're prevail, either by Pope or Spell,</l>
               <l>Of Magick Art, or any Deviliſh Plot,</l>
               <l>They all ſhall ſtink, and burn, and die, and rot.</l>
               <l>When e're they ſhall attempt my Churches weal</l>
               <l>To undermine, I'le ring them ſuch a Peal</l>
               <l>Of thundring Volleys, that ſhall ſtraightway make</l>
               <l>Them quake for fear, or elſe pray do not take</l>
               <l>My Royal Word again, but ſay I am Evil,</l>
               <l>And Pope and I are Partners with the Devil,</l>
               <l>Which Heavens forbid, that ever ſuch a race</l>
               <l>Should ſpring from thence, and after ſome ſmall ſpace.</l>
               <l>Of his return again, ſhould ſtraight proclaim</l>
               <l>Rebells to all that draw in <hi>Charles</hi> his Wain,</l>
               <l>And will not buckle to our develliſh pride</l>
               <l>Of Popery and Slavery, to Ropes they ſhall be tide,</l>
               <l>Or elſe old <hi>Smithfield</hi> flames ſhall them devour,</l>
               <l>To mount us up unto our ſtately Tower,</l>
               <l>Of pride, ambition, avarice, and blood,</l>
               <l>Treaſon, rebellion, faction, a ſweeping floud</l>
               <l>Of Lyes, and Forgeries, Blaſphemies and all,</l>
               <l>'Gainſt <hi>Magna Charta</hi> Laws of Heavens <hi>Whitehall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here ſtop, thou doting fool, and do not think</l>
               <l>At thy deceits and jugling tricks I'le winck,</l>
               <l>For ever and a day, It's time to work when you</l>
               <l>Attempt to poyſon King and Kingdoms too,</l>
               <l>By your pernicious Councels, Witneſs of late,</l>
               <l>The many Loyal Preſents you anticipate,</l>
               <l>And will not let thoſe Loyal Subjects ſee</l>
               <l>With their own eyes, Oh Monſtrous Prodigie!</l>
               <l>You are the Moles that turn to every ſhape,</l>
               <l>And on our Reaſons would commit a Rape</l>
               <l>And rob us of our Sences, and pretend</l>
               <l>For holy Church you do ſo much contend.</l>
               <l>To free us from all errours and from evil,</l>
               <l>Although your power here is from the Devil.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:59492:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And not from Chriſt, who never gave Commiſſion</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto Saint <hi>Peter</hi> by his holy Miſſion,</l>
               <l>To feed his tender Lambs, but not to kill,</l>
               <l>This was the ſubſtance of his ſacred will,</l>
               <l>Which you pervert, and by your ſoveraign power,</l>
               <l>Inſtead of feeding, you do ſtill devour</l>
               <l>This little Flock for whom he ſpent his blood,</l>
               <l>Although by you it is not underſtood.</l>
               <l>But hark you Rebells, the time will ſhortly come,</l>
               <l>Wherein you muſt receive your fatal doom,</l>
               <l>Of, Go ye curſed into flames of fire,</l>
               <l>With fallen Angels, and your curſed Sire,</l>
               <l>Which you begat, and now for your reward,</l>
               <l>Within his Arms, he ſtrongly will you guard;</l>
               <l>To him I leave you, and your bold Comrades</l>
               <l>Who when on earth did act the Maſquerades,</l>
               <l>Your truſty <hi>Roger</hi>'s makes your ways ſo plain,</l>
               <l>To darken <hi>Goſhen</hi> by their numerous train,</l>
               <l>Of croaking Frogs, ariſing ſtill from Hell,</l>
               <l>To charm poor Lambs, by <hi>Heraclitus</hi> ſpell</l>
               <l>Of ſpight and mallice, and inveterate hate,</l>
               <l>Againſt all thoſe that would preſerve the State</l>
               <l>From ruine and deſtruction. But in this they are,</l>
               <l>So libell'd daily by theſe ſhrubs of War,</l>
               <l>Who arm themſelves with Paper, Ink, and Plume,</l>
               <l>Thoſe innocent Lambs (called <hi>Phans</hi>) for to conſume,</l>
               <l>If poſſibly they can, and will them ſtraight devour,</l>
               <l>When once they come within their verge and power.</l>
               <l>But ſtay bold <hi>Towzers,</hi> People are not blind.</l>
               <l>And though to them you have prov'd ever kind,</l>
               <l>The clean contrary way, as doth appear</l>
               <l>By all your Libels both in front and year;</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill they ſay that of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation,</l>
               <l>You are the <hi>Phans,</hi> and ſtand in admiration</l>
               <l>To ſee how boldly you infect the blood</l>
               <l>of Prince and People, which much like a floud</l>
               <l>Of lofty Billows, purpoſely to drown</l>
               <l>Our Ship, our Pilate, and our Captains Crown.</l>
               <l>Which yet ſits faſt, and firm as Laws can make,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs you poyſon him on purpoſe to partake,</l>
               <l>Of Divine Vengeance, which is coming coming on,</l>
               <l>And near at hand, to pluck you from your throne.</l>
               <l>Which Heavens accompliſh in their own good time,</l>
               <l>I'le wait till then, the Lords time ſhall be mine.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>I am,
<salute>Pope and Adherents, &amp;c.</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humble Servant, but moſt irreconcileable Antagoniſt to diſ-ſerve you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ly helping to pluck down your Kingdom of darkneſs, if by any fair and probable means I can.</hi> Theophilus Rationalis.</signed> 
               <dateline>From my Study <date>
                     <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
